<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter from Sir Levvis Dyve: to the Lord Marquis of New-Castle giveing his Lordship an account of the whole conduct of the Kings affaires in Irland [sic], since the time of the Lord Marquis of Ormond, His Excellencies arrival there out of France in Septem. 1648. Until Sr. Lewis his departure out of that Kingdome, in June 1650. Together with the annexed coppies of sundry letters mentioned by Sr. Lewis Dyve as relating to the businesse he treats of from the Hauge 10. 20. July 1650.</title>
            <author>Dyve, Lewis, Sir, 1599-1669.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1650</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 183 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 40 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A81959</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D2979</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E616_7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206730</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865839</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865839</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118090</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A81959)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118090)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 94:E616[7])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter from Sir Levvis Dyve: to the Lord Marquis of New-Castle giveing his Lordship an account of the whole conduct of the Kings affaires in Irland [sic], since the time of the Lord Marquis of Ormond, His Excellencies arrival there out of France in Septem. 1648. Until Sr. Lewis his departure out of that Kingdome, in June 1650. Together with the annexed coppies of sundry letters mentioned by Sr. Lewis Dyve as relating to the businesse he treats of from the Hauge 10. 20. July 1650.</title>
                  <author>Dyve, Lewis, Sir, 1599-1669.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>56; 23, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Samuell Broun, English Bookseller,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Hague :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1650.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>'The copies of the severall letters' has its own caption title, pagination, and register.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Nou: 17".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  II, --  King of England, 1630-1685 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Ireland --  History --  1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118090:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A LETTER FROM S<hi rend="sup">R</hi>. LEVVIS DYVE to the Lord <hi>Marquis of New-Caſtle</hi> gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veing his Lordship an account of the whole Conduct of the KINGS <hi>affaires</hi> in <hi>Irland,</hi> ſince the time of the Lord <hi>Marquis of Ormond,</hi> His <hi>Excellencies</hi> ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rivall there out of <hi>France</hi> in <hi>Septem.</hi> 1648. Until <hi>S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Lewis</hi> his departure out of that Kingdome, In <hi>June</hi> 1650.</p>
            <p>Together with the annexed Coppies of ſundry Letters mentioned by S<hi rend="sup">R</hi>. LEWIS DYVE as relating to the Buſineſſe He treats of <hi>From the</hi> Hague 10./20. July 1650.</p>
            <p>HAGVE, Printed by SAMUELL BROUN, English Bookeſeller. 1650.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:118090:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:118090:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>NOt long after my arrivall at the <hi>Hague,</hi> intimation was given me by a noble freind (upon ſome caſuall diſcourſe with him of the affaires of <hi>Ireland)</hi> that your <hi>Lordship</hi> had a great deſire to be ſatisfied as well in ſome particulars touching the conduct of that buſineſſe ſince my <hi>L<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. Leiu<hi rend="sup">t</hi>.</hi> laſt went thither, as in what condition the <hi>Kingdom</hi> ſtood at the time when I came from thence; Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon not knowing whether the neceſſitie of my occaſions, (or indeed the uſuall thwartneſſe of my fortune in what I moſt covet) would allow me ſo great a hapineſs as perſonally to waite upon you before I left this country, I held it my duty in that caſe to leave ſome teſtimony behind me of my obedience, and readineſſe to ſerve you, wherin rather then faile, I have adventured to ingage my ſelfe in this relation, though cons<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious of mine owne diſability to performe it in ſuch ſort as the ſubject requires, the unpollished rudeneſſe of ſo plaine and courſe a ſtile, affording no luſtre of ornament, or beauty that may render it worthy to be preſented to a perſon of your eminency; which may the eaſier in my behalfe admit of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe, whoſe profeſſion, and practice hath all wayes bin ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed rather to uſe a ſword then a pen: the only plea I have therfore to offer to your Lordship for this preſumption is the candor, and integrity where with it is written, which I have
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:118090:3"/> religiouſly obſerved through the whole body of the diſcourſe, endeavouring to vindicate truth, which I find highly ſuffering by the world, either through the malice, and malignity of theſe unhappy times, or for want of cleare, and impartiall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation: which I am confident your Lordship, and all who rightly know me, will expect from my hands, and which ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely I promiſe to afford, without ſuffering the Biaſſe of any paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, or privat reſpect, or intereſt whatſoever to ſway me in the leaſt circumſtance contrary to truth; unleſſe by miſapre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion, and want of judgment, or by the miſrepreſentation of the ableſt, and beſt knowing perſons, I may unhappily have bin miſled. But, that I may the better do it, it will be neceſſary a little to look back, and take a short view of the deſperate time, wherein his <hi>Ex<hi rend="sup">cy</hi>.</hi> the <hi>Marqueſſe of Ormond,</hi> under tooke this worke; and to reflect upon the ſad face that was then upon <hi>His</hi> MAjESTIES <hi>affaires</hi> in all his three Kingdomes.</p>
            <p>In <hi>England</hi> as your Lordship may well remember, the <hi>King</hi> was not only made a cloſe priſoner, his Crowne, his life, and the ſucceſſion of his poſterity declared againſt, but alſo all thoſe parties that ſtood for him there, or had declared in his behalfe, and taken armes for his reſcue, were wholy diſperſed, and ſubdued: yea and all other men, whoſe parts, honeſty, or pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blique intereſt made them worthy of a ſuſpition, either im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned, banisht, or utterly diſarmed.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Scotland</hi> the army raiſed for the freedome, and reſtaura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the King, having bin unfortunatly loſt (under the leading of <hi>Duke Hamilton</hi> in <hi>Lankashire,)</hi> all that acted by the <hi>Kings</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion were not only compelld to lay downe armes, but after being declared incapable to ſit any more in <hi>Parliament,</hi> or to have any share in Government, ſom of them proſcribed, and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:118090:3"/> expelled the land: whilſt <hi>Cromwell</hi> for having countenanced them in theſe proceedings, was ſaluted at <hi>Edenburgh,</hi> Preſervator of the nation; thus you ſee there are two Kingdoms, wherin is neither Garriſon, nor army left at the <hi>Kings</hi> devotion; nor any perſon ſcarce at liberty, that durſt owne either <hi>him</hi> or his quarrell.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ireland</hi> only remaines to be conſidered, and that God knowes a wofull ſpectacle, cantonized into ſeverall ſundry factions, drawing all divers waies, and driueing on ſeverall intereſts; there was <hi>Iones, Monke,</hi> and <hi>Coote</hi> playing an <hi>Independant</hi> game as eagerly as might be; there were the <hi>Scots</hi> Patronizinge the <hi>Covenant,</hi> and <hi>Presbitery;</hi> there was <hi>O Neale,</hi> and the <hi>Nuntiated</hi> party of the <hi>Cleargy,</hi> that with might, and maine (under the colour of Religion,) were promoteing a <hi>forraigne intereſt,</hi> in caſe they could not make a <hi>Prince</hi> at home; there was the <hi>counſell of the confederats,</hi> together with all the auntient <hi>English,</hi> and ſome of the <hi>Irish</hi> their adherents (who being more moderat, and averſe to ſuch deſperat courſes, awakened alſo with the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries that oppreſt them already, &amp; the ruin that menaced them out of <hi>England)</hi> made fresh applications into <hi>France,</hi> unto the <hi>Queene,</hi> and the <hi>Prince his highneſſe,</hi> that my <hi>Lord Leiu<hi rend="sup">t</hi>.</hi> and the <hi>Kings Authority</hi> might againe be ſent amongſt them; wherupon theſe two factions grew to ſo great a fewde, that the latter were all <hi>excomunicated</hi> by the firſt; and the firſt proclaimed <hi>Traytors</hi> by the latter.</p>
            <p>Beſides all theſe, there was <hi>Inchiquin,</hi> who having recol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected himſelfe at laſt, &amp; diſlikeing the revolutions in <hi>England,</hi> had prevailed with his party, to declare for the <hi>King.</hi> Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he made a <hi>ceſſation</hi> with the <hi>counſell of the confederats,</hi> in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of my <hi>Lord Leiu<hi rend="sup">ts</hi>,</hi> coming over; which <hi>ceſſation</hi> being
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:118090:4"/> violently oppoſed, both by the ſpirituall, and temporall ſword of the <hi>Nuntio,</hi> and <hi>O Neale,</hi> induced finally my Lord <hi>Marqueſs of Clanricard,</hi> (who from the time of my <hi>Lord Leiu<hi rend="sup">nts</hi>.</hi> going to ſea from <hi>Dublin,</hi> had retired himſelfe, and his family to a place convenient to ship away: aſſoone as he should deſpaire of being able to ſerve the <hi>King</hi> by his further ſtay) to take armes, and drawe together his army to countenance the <hi>ceſſation,</hi> and to make way for my Lord <hi>Marqueſs of Ormond</hi> with the <hi>Kings Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority;</hi> to which he did highly contribute, by awing, and curbing the towne of <hi>Galloway,</hi> at that time the ſeat of the <hi>Nuntio,</hi> and the principall receptacle of the moſt factious people in the Kingdome; as alſo by his ſuccesfull reduceing of <hi>Fort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faukland, Athlone, Iames towne,</hi> and the greateſt part of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince into his power; But to the end that you may ſee with what ſteadineſſe that <hi>Honorable Perſon</hi> in the depth of all theſe <hi>revolutions</hi> hath ſtill adhered unto the ſervice of the <hi>King</hi> and the Intereſts, of the <hi>Crown</hi> even againſt thoſe that couloured al their deſignes and practiſes over, with the artificialleſt and moſt deludeing pretences of <hi>Religion</hi> (ſince it is an example fit to be recommended to poſterity and truly worthy your lordships knowledge) you may pleaſe to read the particular conduct of this his undertakeing in the Coppy of a Letter (I ſend you herewithall) writ from the <hi>Marquis</hi> himſelfe to <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſingham</hi> then in <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this poſture was <hi>Ireland</hi> when my <hi>Lord Leiu<hi rend="sup">t</hi>.</hi> came againe upon the ſtage; with his hands in effect empty of armes, and his purſe of money, without the countenance, or aſſiſtance of any <hi>foraigne ſtate,</hi> wherby to unite this diſtracted people, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover unto His MAjESTIE this devided Kingdome; before <hi>Cromwell</hi> were at leaſure, to make an expedition thither, which
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:118090:4"/> as yet either the <hi>murder</hi> of the <hi>King</hi> not yet perpetrated, or the unſettlement of that <hi>mishapen cub</hi> of his <hi>new common wealth</hi> detained him from.</p>
            <p>Yet notwithſtanding all theſe diſadvantages of having neither armes wherwith to awe, or money wherwith to buy men into their duty, or any party ready to imbrace him (my Lord of <hi>Clanricard</hi> only excepted) but upon the racke of ſcrewed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions; yet at length by Gods bleſſing and his owne prudent management of affaires, ioyned with the great intereſt he had in that people, he ordered matters ſo, as in few months to ſowlder moſt of theſe factions together; and make <hi>a peace,</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto all but <hi>O Neale,</hi> and the <hi>Independant</hi> party did willingly ſubmit. <hi>O Neale</hi> complained that the conditions were neither ſafe, nor large enough, as to the concernments of Religion, and the Province of <hi>Vlſter:</hi> and the <hi>Independant</hi> party exclaimed that the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Religion, and the <hi>English intereſt</hi> forſooth were both betrayed by it: ſo opoſite were, then, theſe two par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in their publique quarrells, about the peace, who you shall ſee not long after shake hands behind the curtaine againſt the <hi>Kings Authority,</hi> which indeed is the blocke they both ſtumble at; for as to the pretence of <hi>Religion</hi> in the firſt, it is manifeſt how vaine it was, for you shall find that party embrace the peace herafter upon the very ſame conditions; And as to their <hi>Provinciall</hi> concernments, they were even then well enough ſatisfied that my <hi>Lord Leiu<hi rend="sup">t</hi>.</hi> could in no ſort be blamed, he being put upon the choiſe whether he would accept of the reſt of the <hi>confederats,</hi> and the <hi>English</hi> party in <hi>Monſter</hi> upon the termes in the printed articles, without any further conceſſions unto <hi>Owen O Neale,</hi> and the <hi>Vlſter</hi> army: or elſe in yeelding to their demaunds, looſe both the other two; which may ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:118090:5"/> to juſtify my <hi>Lord Leiu<hi rend="sup">t</hi>.</hi> in that peace againſt their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints. The invectives of <hi>Co<hi rend="sup">ll</hi>. Jones,</hi> &amp; his party were urged with far greater arte, and fallacies, which being induſtriouſly published in <hi>print,</hi> were received, I feare, with too much ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe by many of the people of <hi>England,</hi> that either were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing, or unable to judge a right; and being fortified by a <hi>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall animoſitie,</hi> had too great an influence, even in <hi>Ireland</hi> it ſelfe, upon the <hi>English</hi> army under the comand of my Lord <hi>Inchiquin;</hi> wherin ſundry of the principall Officers were ſo averſe to a conjunction with the <hi>Irish,</hi> that dureing the time of the <hi>treaty</hi> they conſpired to have ſurprized both my <hi>Lord Leiu<hi rend="sup">t</hi>.</hi> and the <hi>Lord Preſident,</hi> &amp; to have delivered them up to the <hi>Parliament:</hi> which in all probabillity had then taken effect, had it not bien acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentally prevented by their unexpected departure from <hi>Caricke,</hi> upon a petition, or repreſentation from the counſell of the <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federat Catholiques</hi> to <hi>His Ex<hi rend="sup">cy</hi>.</hi> that he would remove thence to his owne houſe at <hi>Kilkeny;</hi> as a place more fit for the conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the <hi>treaty:</hi> Now whether thoſe ſons of <hi>Zerviah</hi> were ſo ſtrong, and powerfull in the <hi>army</hi> that they could not be called to an account, or whether it was conceived more conducible for the advancement of <hi>His</hi> MAjESTIES <hi>affaires</hi> to reduce them with time, and gentleneſſe to a right underſtanding, then to looſe ſo many perſons of abillity, and authority, I know not, only I feare their impunity was either the ſole, or concurrent cauſe of the generall revolt, and apoſtacy of thoſe garriſons ſince. But for a full, and ſatisfactory anſwer to all objections, that can be made by either of the parties upon that ſubject, I have taken the bouldneſſe to ſend your <hi>Lordship</hi> together with this, the copy of a letter (I found lying by me) that was writ by <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Walſingham,</hi> in returne to the laſt of <hi>Jones</hi> his printed papers,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:118090:5"/> (after it was thought fit by my <hi>Lord Leiu<hi rend="sup">t</hi>.</hi> to reply no more as from himſelfe) which ſpeaks ſo much truth, and reaſon, that though it came to <hi>Jones</hi> his hands, he was well content to give over his paper war; in that letter your <hi>Lordship</hi> may find the peace ſo firmely aſſerted, and both the juſtice, and neceſſity of what was don ſo well demonſtrated, as wauing all arguments of mine owne in that behalfe I refer you <hi>Lordship</hi> thither for an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire ſatisfaction.</p>
            <p>Only I shall take leave to tell your <hi>Lordship</hi> this, that his <hi>Ex<hi rend="sup">cy</hi>.</hi> in aſſociating the <hi>Irish</hi> and my Lord of <hi>Inchiquin</hi> together, and in making up of this <hi>peace,</hi> hath what in conditions to the one, and to the other, ſo bound up himſelfe, as he may well be ſaid to be <hi>Lord Leiu<hi rend="sup">t</hi>.</hi> but upon curteſy, untill the time of <hi>Parliament;</hi> having granted unto my Lord <hi>Inchiquin</hi> the ſole co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, and ordering of thoſe forces, and garriſons he brought with him to the <hi>Kings</hi> obedience; and having oblidged him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe unto the confederats to authorize only thoſe Officers, and to march in the head of that army which their <hi>Commiſsioners</hi> should preſent unto him. By this your <hi>Lordship</hi> may perceive the neceſſity unto which His <hi>Ex<hi rend="sup">cy</hi>.</hi> was brought, but it could not be avoided, either theſe thinges muſt be aſſented unto by him, or the <hi>peace</hi> muſt not be made.</p>
            <p>And in this ſort my <hi>Lord Liu<hi rend="sup">nt</hi>s.</hi> hands were manacled in ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect as to the <hi>militia,</hi> he having no more to do, but only to go in, &amp; out before an army of ſeverall <hi>factions,</hi> &amp; <hi>religions</hi> much averſe to one another: the Officers wherof though never ſo much diſliked by him he could not but admit of; if either the one party, or the other inſiſted upon their conditions; it cannot therfore ſeeme ſtrange, (when rightly conſidered,) that <hi>Inchiquins,</hi> and the <hi>Irish</hi> forces were never incorporated together,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:118090:6"/> nor indifferently intermingled in all the garriſons; neither why the army was either ſo ill diſciplined, and officerd, (as in truth it was,) ſince what hath bin ſaid is a full anſwer, as I conceive, to that objection.</p>
            <p>The difficulties His <hi>Ex<hi rend="sup">cy</hi>.</hi> alſo had, to make theſe ſeverall <hi>Factions</hi> underſtand either him, or one another, were very great; witnes the printed <hi>Declaration</hi> the <hi>Mounſter</hi> forces ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torted from him before the concluſion of the <hi>peace,</hi> and thoſe many diffidences, and demurs the <hi>Irish</hi> made therupon; both which parties he muſt of neceſſity humor, and comply with, or elſe mutinies, and defections could not be avoided. The caſe being ſuch, your <hi>Lordship</hi> (who have commanded great ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and had experience in ſome meaſure of theſe inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences) very well knowes, that the skill muſt needs be great in a <hi>Generall</hi> ſo to devide himſelfe amongſt them, as to keep them in obedience, and contented. My <hi>Lord Lieu<hi rend="sup">t</hi>.</hi> by the gentleneſſe, and affabilitie of his diſpoſition, and his great pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in foreſeeing, &amp; preuenting evils, wreſtled a long time ſuccesfully, with all theſe inconveniences, tuneing all theſe diſcords into harmony; and at length aſſoone as money could be got to move withall, or the ground affoorded graſſe for their horſe, a part of the army is drawn together under the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of the <hi>Earle of Caſtle-haven</hi> (generall of the horſe) whoſe prevaileing againſt ſeverall of <hi>O Neales,</hi> &amp; <hi>Jones</hi> his garriſons joyned to the voluntary coming in of many of their ſouldiers, and ſurrender of their holds, gave very much credit, and repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to the <hi>Kings army.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All the time that this is in doing my <hi>Lord Leiu<hi rend="sup">t</hi>.</hi> was buſied in treating with, and courting <hi>Jones,</hi> &amp; <hi>Owen O Neale</hi> unto the <hi>Kings</hi> obedience; the firſt of which (being as is beleived)
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:118090:6"/> corrupted by <hi>Cromwells</hi> bribes, &amp; large promiſes, poſitively de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clines my <hi>Lord Leiu<hi rend="sup">ts</hi>.</hi> favour, as apeares by their <hi>printed</hi> let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters: the latter having at laſt waued all things concerning re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, more then what was granted in the <hi>peace,</hi> inſiſts finally upon the comand of 6000. foot, and 800. horſe, together with thoſe other conditions that ſince were granted him; the <hi>Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners</hi> will permit my <hi>Lord Leiu<hi rend="sup">t</hi>.</hi> to allow him no more but 4000. foot &amp; 600. horſe, which number they obſtinatly refuſed to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed; denying him alſo ſeveral other of his leſſer demaunds, wherupon <hi>O Neale</hi> ſeeing them willing either to leave him quite out, or to have him come in upon ſuch termes as he judged inconſiderable, (they peradventure thinking themſelves able to do the worke without him) makes preſent application unto <hi>Monk,</hi> and <hi>Jones,</hi> either to be revenged, upon the <hi>Commiſsioners,</hi> my Lord of <hi>Inchiquin,</hi> the <hi>Scots,</hi> and all the reſt, that he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived to oppoſe him, or elſe, as he afterwards ſaid, to make himſelfe more conſiderable, and therby facilitate his condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions with them.</p>
            <p>Whatſoever his motive was, at laſt <hi>Monke</hi> makes an agreement with him, in the name of the <hi>Parliament;)</hi> though they very tamely upon <hi>Cromwells</hi> motion did afterwards thinke fit to diſclaime him) upon which ſcore, howſoever, he aſſiſted them all he could, undertaking the releife of <hi>Derry,</hi> which he after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards effected; and notwithſtanding that his <hi>Ex<hi rend="sup">cy</hi>.</hi> dureing all this time was very ſencible of the great conſequence of <hi>Owen O Neales</hi> comming in, or ſtanding out, in order to the ſervice, or diſſervice of the <hi>King,</hi> and that he looked upon the diſpute of denying him the comand of 6000. men, when they were content to entruſt him with 4000. as a ſtrange kind of overſight in the <hi>Commiſsioners,</hi> &amp; the reſt concurring with them, the rather,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:118090:7"/> becauſe he knew that by his ſtanding out, that accurſed quarrell betweene the <hi>Kings,</hi> and the <hi>Nuntios</hi> party, (not unlike that of the <hi>Guelphs,</hi> and <hi>Gibbelines</hi> in <hi>Italy)</hi> was kept on foot, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fractory Cleargy were countenanced, &amp; upheld in credit with the people, and the great <hi>Cityes</hi> were animated to refuſe guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſons, to deny the payment of impoſitions, and to diſreſpect both the <hi>Lord Leiu<hi rend="sup">t</hi>,</hi> and the <hi>Commiſsioners:</hi> yet was it not in his power to helpe it by any meanes; unleſſe he would have broken conditions with them, which no conſideration of any advantage, how great ſoever, could induce him to do, ſo tender hath he bin ever of his faith and engagements given: The buſines being grown paſt remedy, he gives the treaty over, and the ſeaſon inviteing him to take the field, his army being drawen together, he bends his thoughts wholy now upon the reduction of <hi>Dublin,</hi> yet meetes with a very unexpected rub in the beginning of his march, for the <hi>English</hi> forces of <hi>Mounſter</hi> would not move, neither would the <hi>Vlſter Scots</hi> unanimouſly ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit before my Lord <hi>Inchiquin</hi> be declared <hi>Leiu<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Generall</hi> of the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my: which comand had bin imediatly upon the <hi>peace</hi> conferd on my Lord Marqueſſe of <hi>Clanricard</hi> (now upon his march towards <hi>Slego)</hi> but this demur was alſo overcom by his Lordships being content, to part with <hi>that comand,</hi> rather then the <hi>Kings</hi> ſervice should ſuffer through any concernment of his: ſoon after my Lord of <hi>Caſtle-haven,</hi> upon my Lord of <hi>Inchiquins</hi> horſe refuſeing to obey his orders, quits the feild in diſtaſte, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tires to <hi>Kilkeny;</hi> which his <hi>Ex<hi rend="sup">cy</hi>.</hi> ſeemed willing for avoiding greater inconveniences to ſuffer, giving the Earle of <hi>Caſtle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haven</hi> the charge of ſeing the contributions brought in, and the Comand of the country in his abſence.</p>
            <p>Theſe difficulties overcome, His <hi>Ex<hi rend="sup">cy</hi>.</hi> makes directly for
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:118090:7"/> 
               <hi>Dublin,</hi> all the garriſons in his way (but <hi>Balliſonan)</hi> by force, or faire meanes ſurrendring to him, yet is he ſet forth ſo ſlenderly provided with money, that neare <hi>Kildare</hi> the army is ready to mutiny, &amp; fall to peeces for want of a very ſmall ſumm, had not a worthy perſon (that was there but accidentally) ſupplied them in that extremity; this ſtraight alſo being overpaſt, &amp; my Lord of <hi>Inchiquins</hi> forces being come wholy up, they hold on for <hi>Dublin,</hi> and compell <hi>Jones</hi> that was drawne out as far as the <hi>Naas</hi> with what ſtrength he could make to interupt them, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire into the towne; whither being come at laſt, and finding it competently well fortified, and plentifullie man'd both with horſe, and foot, in ſo much that it was judged no waies fit to hazard the army upon a deſperat aſſault, and being not as yet a number able to inveſt the place, eſpecially whilſt <hi>O Neale,</hi> and <hi>Monke,</hi> together with the garriſons of <hi>Drogheda,</hi> and <hi>Trim</hi> lay ſo convenient to attempt upon them; it was reſolved that my <hi>Lord Leiu<hi rend="sup">t</hi>.</hi> should with the greateſt part of his army encampe at <hi>Finglaſſe,</hi> from thence to awe, &amp; diſtreſſe the towne, and be ready to countenance any ſtirs, or revolts within, whilſt my Lord of <hi>Inchiquin</hi> with a great body of horſe, and above 2000 foot endevours to take in <hi>Trim,</hi> and <hi>Drogheda;</hi> al this time <hi>His Ex<hi rend="sup">cy</hi>.</hi> found great <hi>wants</hi> to encounter with, his proviſions, and contributions coming in ſo ſlowly, and diſproportionably to the neceſſities of his army; and many <hi>factions</hi> to compoſe, and temper, the <hi>Mounſter,</hi> and the reſt of the <hi>English</hi> forces mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muring againſt the liberty the <hi>Irish</hi> had there in the exerciſe of their religion, &amp; the <hi>Irish</hi> againe repining to ſee themſelves mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mured at; but more eſpecially to ſee the <hi>English Mounſter</hi> forces (though they were fewer in number, and had contributions of their owne) to ſwallow up both their pay, and proviſions alſo;
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:118090:8"/> which though the reſt of the army did petition againſt, <hi>His Ex<hi rend="sup">cy</hi>.</hi> could in no waies remedy, being conſtrained to humor, and comply with that party, as being a people ſo ticklish, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteady, that, if diſguſted, might probably either ſide with <hi>Jones,</hi> or retireing to their own garriſons, compell the army to with draw, from <hi>Dublin</hi> by declaring themſelves for the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Tho. Armſtronge,</hi> and my <hi>Lord Moore</hi> being come in to my Lord <hi>Inchiquin; Co<hi rend="sup">ll</hi>. Mark Treuors</hi> (that was but newly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared for the <hi>King)</hi> having got notice of a choice party of <hi>O Neales,</hi> ſent to <hi>Dundalke</hi> to convay thence ſuch armes, and amu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition as <hi>Monk</hi> had undertaken to ſuply him withall, invites my Lord <hi>Inchiquin</hi> to intercept them, who came ſo oportunely thither, that he gained <hi>O Neals</hi> ſuplie of amunition, with the utter defeat of his party; wherupon ſoon after the gaining of <hi>Drogedah,</hi> which enſued imediatly upon <hi>O Neales</hi> defeat; <hi>Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalke</hi> it ſelfe being ſummoned, the ſouldiers compelled <hi>Monk</hi> to a ſurrender, and themſelves took armes for the <hi>King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Imediatly after this defeat of his party, <hi>O Neale</hi> haſtneth towards the releife of <hi>Derry</hi> which was the only towne in that <hi>Province</hi> untaken, all the reſt being already reduced by the Lord of <hi>Ards, S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. George Monro,</hi> and <hi>Co<hi rend="sup">ll</hi>. Treuors,</hi> who were now hindered only by <hi>O Neales</hi> army, and the Siedg of <hi>Derry,</hi> from bringing up a conſiderable body of horſe, and foot to the leaguer of <hi>Dublin.</hi> Where may be obſerved how great a preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice the faction of thoſe men (who deſireing out of animoſities, &amp; ends of their owne, to ſtaue of <hi>O Neal</hi> &amp; his party from the benefit of the peace; ſtood chaffering with him about his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mande of 4000, or 6000. men, and other trifles) have don to the <hi>Kinges</hi> ſervice, and to the whole <hi>Kingdomes</hi> in deprivinge
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:118090:8"/> themſelves therby, not only of the forementioned aſſiſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of the <hi>Scots,</hi> but alſo of the poſſeſſion of <hi>London Derry,</hi> together with ſo conſiderable an addition of forces as <hi>O Neale</hi> could then have brought; wherby not only the whole Province of <hi>Vlſter</hi> would have bin ſecured to the <hi>King;</hi> but <hi>Dublin</hi> it ſelfe either reduced, or ſo ſtrongly furrounded, that it would have bin impoſſible either for <hi>Jones</hi> to releive himſelfe, or <hi>Cromwell</hi> to invade the Kingdom: which, notwithſtanding all theſe fore mentioned diſadvantages, was, upon the matter, even gained already, and would have bin entirely, without any manner of queſtion, if it had fortuned that His MAjESTIE had feaſonably come thither himſelfe in perſon, which by all parties was deſired with infinit paſſion, but eſpecially by thoſe whoſe prudence made them beſt able to judge how effectuall his preſence would be, not only for the animating of his own loiall party, but alſo ſuppreſſing of all factious humors, and uniteing all intereſts chearfully, &amp; unanimouſly to go on againſt the <hi>common enemy:</hi> which muſt ſoon have put a period to that warr, and made his authority abſolut in that <hi>Kingdom,</hi> without diſpute; for as upon his arrivall His MAjESTIE should have found <hi>Mounſter</hi> enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely in the <hi>Irish,</hi> and my Lord of <hi>Inchiquins</hi> poſſeſſion, <hi>Vlſter</hi> all reduced, but the fort of <hi>Culmore,</hi> and <hi>Derry</hi> into the hands of the <hi>Scots; Conaght</hi> by the Marqueſs of <hi>Clanrieards</hi> fortunate gaining the ſtrong fort of <hi>Slego</hi> (with what elſe the enemy had then remaining in that <hi>Province)</hi> wholy cleared: in <hi>Leinſter</hi> nothing left for <hi>rebellion</hi> to neſtle in, but <hi>Dublin</hi> &amp; <hi>Balliſonnan;</hi> both which were ſo well attended upon, that the defendants had but little pleaſure to ayre themſelves without the circuit of their workes; ſo by his coming he would undoubtedly have diverted <hi>Owen O Neale</hi> (who would imediatly have ſubmitted unto the perſon
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:118090:9"/> of the <hi>King</hi> from releiving <hi>London Derry,</hi> and therby have ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured both that town, and Province, with <hi>Dublin</hi> alſo as it is thought) for they that had reaſon to know <hi>Jones</hi> his mind apprehended that his leaving the <hi>Kings</hi> party did proceede from a <hi>Pique</hi> either againſt my <hi>Lord Leiu<hi rend="sup">t</hi>.</hi> or <hi>S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Robert Byron</hi> about a <hi>Leiu<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Co<hi rend="sup">lls</hi>.</hi> place, which was conferd over his head upon an other; and that then the ſcene being altered in <hi>England,</hi> &amp; his old freinds out of authority there, his new termes with the <hi>Independents</hi> alſo yet unmade, he had himſelfe come over, if the <hi>King</hi> had bin there in perſon; or if not, yet his <hi>party</hi> would have all deſerted him; and the worke had bin don one way, or other; that <hi>Kingdom</hi> wholy reduced without ablow; all factions, as I ſaid before extinguisht; and His MAjESTIE had an army of above 20000. men to have emploied where he pleaſed.</p>
            <p>However, thitherto you ſee my <hi>Lord Leiu<hi rend="sup">t</hi>.</hi> (having ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented together ſo many differing parties, &amp; maſtered almoſt incredible difficulties) hath with prudence, and ſucceſſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducted the buſines, and is hindered only by the wilfulnes, and faction of ſome of his owne party from compleating the worke. After the taking in of <hi>Trim</hi> (which followed ſoon upon the ſurrender of <hi>Dundalke,)</hi> my Lord of <hi>Inchiquin</hi> brings up his forces, now much improved in number, to the army before <hi>Dublin</hi> wherupon His <hi>Ex<hi rend="sup">cy</hi>.</hi> leaving a part of his army at <hi>Caſtle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knock</hi> under the Command of my Lord <hi>Dillon</hi> of <hi>Coſtelo</hi> (a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of much gallantry) to keepe them in on that ſide the water, removes his <hi>Campe</hi> to the other ſide the towne, to diſtreſſe the enemy that way alſo, which, whilſt they are endevouring to do, (upon intelligence that <hi>Cromwell</hi> was ready with an army to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barke himſelfe for <hi>Ireland,</hi> and that he intended to land in <hi>Mounſter)</hi> my Lord of <hi>Inchiquin</hi> thought it fit that he should
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:118090:9"/> with a good party of horſe go down into thoſe parts to ſecure his garriſons and provide for the worſt.</p>
            <p>His <hi>Lordship</hi> was no ſooner gone, but my <hi>Lord Leiu<hi rend="sup">t</hi>.</hi> deſigning to shut up the enemy within his workes, and quite impede as well their getting in of hay, as the graſeing of their cattle with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out their line; gave order to <hi>Patrick Purcell,</hi> Major Generall of the foot, to march with a ſufficient party of men, and an Engineer to <hi>Baggot-Rath</hi> there to poſſeſſe himſelfe of that place immediatly, &amp; caſt up ſuch a worke as had been already de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned: <hi>S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. William Vaughan</hi> Commiſſary Generall of the horſe, had order likewiſe to draw together moſt part of the troopes that were on that ſide the water and to keepe them in a body upon a large plowed field looking towards the Caſtle of <hi>Dublin,</hi> there to countenance the foot whilſt the workes were finishing, and to ſecure them in caſe the enemy out of the towne should attempt to interrupt them. Theſe (my <hi>Lord)</hi> were the orders given, but not executed, for notwithſtanding it did not much exceed a mile, whither the foot were to go, yet through the ignorance, or negligence of the Officers, that were to conduct them many houres were ſpent, ere they came at the place: Whither when they were come they found the worke ſo wretchleſly advanced by <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Welsh</hi> the Engineer, (and to helpe all) themſelves kept ſuch negligent guards, that many judged it was done on purpoſe; &amp; that theſe neglects proceeded from thoſe lurking ſeedes of diſcord betwene the <hi>Kings</hi> and the <hi>Nuntios</hi> parties: for it is certaine that about that time upon an apprehenſion that thinges went on too proſperouſly with my <hi>Lord Leiu<hi rend="sup">t</hi>.</hi> there were Letters written to <hi>Owen O Neale,</hi> about broaching a new warr, in caſe <hi>Dublin</hi> had bin taken; what ever the grounds of theſe faileings were, the enemy never ſtood to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:118090:10"/> examin, but being much troubled to ſee <hi>a fort</hi> deſigning there, (where, with ſo much eaſe they might not only be kept, from all forrage, and ſuccour by land, but entercourſe with the ſea alſo:) and perceiving the poſture they were in, deſtitute of horſe, to guard them, reſolues upon a deſperat ſally to diſturb this worke, which they hapned to make about eight of the clock in the morning, when His <hi>Ex<hi rend="sup">cy</hi>.</hi> who had bin on horſeback moſt part of the night (as his conſtant cuſtome was ſince his coming neare <hi>Dublin)</hi> was newly laide him down in his tent to take his reſt.</p>
            <p>The enemy found the new fortification ſo ſlight, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance there ſo weake, that they ſoon became maſters of the place, from whence ſeeing the <hi>Irish</hi> flie in ſuch fright &amp; diſorder, (contrary to their firſt intentions,) they purſued them up to the avenewes of their <hi>Campe,</hi> where finding the ſouldiers alſo that were in gard with great ſecuritie, and unconcernment looking on, they laid hold on the advantage, charging briskly in, and in a trice beat them of their poſts, which if they had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended (as a far leſs number then they were, might very eaſily have don) the <hi>Campe</hi> being no way acceſſible towards the towne, (excepting by thoſe few avenewes which there purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſely had been left open, nay ſome of them thrown open con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to orders for the conveniency of the ſoldiers) could poſſibly have run no hazard.</p>
            <p>But theſe paſſes being thus loſt, &amp; abandoned, &amp; more men coming out of the towne to reinforce thoſe that were alredy ſo ſuccesfull, the whole army in the greateſt terror, and confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion that might be, falls a running every one a ſeverall way, &amp; in this condition were all things brought before my Lord <hi>Taaffe</hi> then Generall of the <hi>Ordinance</hi> had awaked my <hi>Lord Leiu<hi rend="sup">t</hi>.,</hi> who
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:118090:10"/> preſently takeing horſe together with my Lord of <hi>Caſtle-haven</hi> (who was now returned backe to his command) &amp; <hi>Co<hi rend="sup">ll</hi>. Milo Power;</hi> made towards the enemy taking all ſuch a long with them as they could either by force, or faire meanes perſwade to face about, with intention to beat them backe, or at leaſt, by making head a while, to ſtop their progreſſe till ſom conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable part of the army could be rallied, and brought up againe, to oppoſe them: but by that time they came neare the enemy, their followers were grown ſo thin, that <hi>His Ex<hi rend="sup">cy</hi>.</hi> (after the having expoſed himſelfe to much danger, and received a shot upon his armes in a brusk charge that he made upon the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt of the enemies troopes,) was faine to retire at laſt, and ſeeke to recover his army that was gone before; <hi>S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. William Vaughan</hi> being already killed, his brother <hi>Co<hi rend="sup">ll</hi>. Richard Butler</hi> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and the whole campe in effect abandoned except by thoſe that could not get them ready, or wanted meanes of flyinge.</p>
            <p>Thus beſides the ſlaughter that was made, and the priſoners that were taken, one of which was the lot of moſt of the <hi>English</hi> that were under the command of <hi>Co<hi rend="sup">ll</hi>. Woogan</hi> (whoſe behaviour that day deſerves much commendation) who having gotten together into a ſmall body defended themſelves ſo gallantly and with ſo much reſolution againſt the whole power of the enemy, as at laſt, after a great ſlaughter, the reſt made conditions for themfelves before they could be inforced to yeeld, or lay downe armes:) the totall plunder of the campe, with all the artillery, tents, and baggage fell into the enemies hands, moſt of my Lord of <hi>Inchiquins</hi> foot, that at firſt made ſome reſiſtance, ſeing the day loſt, upon this diſaſter changed ſides, and revolted to the enemy. All this was don in ſo short a ſpace, and with ſo little noiſe, that my Lord <hi>Dillon,</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:118090:11"/> and the reſt of the forces that were on the other ſide the river of the <hi>Liffy,</hi> knew nothing of what was don till the buſineſſe was over, and ſome ſcattering runawaies brought him word of it; the <hi>Irish</hi> that got of, made ſuch haſt every one towards his home, and with ſuch diſtraction, that it was impoſſible for my Lord <hi>Leiu<hi rend="sup">t</hi>.</hi> to draw any body of them together; and therfore (having met with the newes of the ſurrender of <hi>Balliſannon</hi> that very day into the hands of his forces that lay before it) he reſted at <hi>Caterlo</hi> that night, and went the next day to confer with the <hi>Commiſsioners of truſt,</hi> and my Lord <hi>Inchiquin</hi> at <hi>Kilkeny.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When this great diſaſter is well conſidered, ſcarce any other ſound reaſon can be given for ſo ſad a misfortune, but the good pleaſure of <hi>Almightie God.</hi> who (if it be lawfull to look ſo far into the judgments of heaven,) knowing the ill intentions and deſignes that were in the harts of many both of the <hi>Irish</hi> and <hi>English</hi> there, in caſe <hi>Dublin</hi> had bin taken, ſaw them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of that bleſſing, and tooke that time, for their punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and humiliation; not only in this but a torrent of other croſſes following in the necke one of another; for beſides this miſchance before <hi>Dublin,</hi> to the ruin of ſo great an army, about the ſame time <hi>O Neale</hi> releives <hi>Coot</hi> in <hi>London Derry,</hi> to the immediat loſſe of that <hi>Province,</hi> &amp; the future ſcourge of his owne followers; not long before likewiſe the <hi>plague</hi> was brought by a ship out of <hi>Spaine</hi> into <hi>Gallway,</hi> and beſides the havock it made in that towne, ſo diſperſt it ſelfe over all the <hi>Province</hi> of <hi>Conaught,</hi> that my Lord <hi>Marqueſs</hi> of <hi>Clanricard;</hi> being deprived thorough the Calamities that were upon that towne, &amp; coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try both of money, and meanes, to march withall, could not for many months draw his army together, either to act any thing alone, or joine with any other, for feare leaſt by that meanes the <hi>plague,</hi> that made ſuch ſpoile while they were aſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, should mow them down when they were all together.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:118090:11"/>
            <p>This Route at <hi>Dublin,</hi> the releife of <hi>Derry,</hi> and the <hi>plague</hi> might be thought competent afflictions to be caſt upon a people ſo impoverished, &amp; a Kingdom ſo waſted before; yet this ſufficeth not, there are heavier loſſes yet to follow, and a worſe <hi>peſtilence</hi> to land shortly at <hi>Dublin,</hi> that will ſweep away their men, and townes together; but here your <hi>Lordship</hi> may juſtly interrupt me, and ſay, that though it muſt be confeſſed, that whatſoever befalls us in this vale of miſery is to be attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted to the hand of heaven, or the permiſſion at leaſt of the devine providence, (into the reaſons of whoſe ſecret, and hidden counſells, our weake capacities are unable to ſearch) yet nevertheleſſe thoſe viſible cauſes, wherby we draw mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes upon our ſelves, by ſuch, who through neglect of their duty, &amp; diſobedience to their ſuperiours, are apparently the authors therof, ought not to paſſe unpunished, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you ſee no reaſon why thoſe were not called to an account that deſerved it both by their cowardice, and ſo shamfull omiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of their duty, as could admit of no excuſe.</p>
            <p>But when your <hi>Lordship</hi> shall be pleaſed to reflect upon what I ſaid before, that my <hi>L<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. Leiu<hi rend="sup">t</hi>.</hi> comands this army, &amp; indeed the <hi>Kingdom</hi> but as it were upon <hi>courteſy,</hi> all his authority in effect con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting in the aweing one faction with another, the beſt of which he found to be on ſo uncertaine, &amp; unſetled, termes; that you will I doubt not when you reflect upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it eaſily grant, that my <hi>L<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. Leiu<hi rend="sup">t</hi>.</hi> could not in prudence do an act that was likely to give ſo great, &amp; generall a diſtaſte as indeede to have proceded againſt the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor Generall</hi> would have bin to the <hi>confederats,</hi> amongſt whom he had ſo many alliances, &amp; freinds: &amp; the running away of the reſt was ſo univerſall a fault, that it was hard to diſcover who deſerved pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t moſt; &amp; harder to find a Court of warr to cenſure them.</p>
            <p>Dureing this short reſidence at <hi>Kilkeny,</hi> His <hi>Ex.<hi rend="sup">cy</hi>:</hi> have<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing taken order with the Lord <hi>Inchiquin</hi> to bring up what
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:118090:12"/> forces he could poſſibly make, and with the Commiſſioners for the recruteing, drawing together, &amp; arming, their diſperſed forces aſſoon as could be, to the end they might be ſent after him, who ſpeeds away himſelfe in the company only of 20 or 30 horſe towards <hi>Trim,</hi> and <hi>Drogheda,</hi> as the places both neareſt the enemies attempts, and likelieſt to totter backe, if not ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured in time: at <hi>Tecroghan</hi> (a houſe of <hi>S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Luke Fitzgarretts)</hi> he makes a ſtay, till thoſe ſeverall bodies that he then expected were com up, and upon notice of their coming removes to <hi>Trim;</hi> where he meets with newes of <hi>Jones</hi> his being before <hi>Drogheda,</hi> who ſoon after, upon intelligence that my <hi>Lord Leiu<hi rend="sup">t</hi>.</hi> was at <hi>Trim,</hi> and ſupoſeing his forces, to be greater then indeed they were, drew of in the night, &amp; returned Ime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly to <hi>Dublin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next day His <hi>Ex<hi rend="sup">cy</hi>.</hi> went through to <hi>Drogheda,</hi> where a party of the <hi>Scotch</hi> horſe, and foot under the Command of the Lord of <hi>Ards,</hi> and the Lord <hi>Clanbrazill.</hi> Came up unto him, but, whilſt they are conſulting what to do, they receive aſſurance of <hi>Cromwells</hi> landing with very conſiderable forces: Wherupon concludeing that towne neceſſary to be kept to entertaine the enemy before whilſt they made up their army, as they hoped to do very conſiderably, &amp; ſoone enough to come to the releife of the place; of which if they should faile, no queſtion was made, but after the gaining of time, which was then pretious, they in the town should be able to make honorable conditions for themſelves; whilſt <hi>Cromwell</hi> is refreshing his own men in <hi>Dublin</hi> and reducing <hi>Jones's,</hi> there is put into <hi>Drogheda</hi> a garriſon of 2500 foot, and 300 horſe, which was thought ſufficient: &amp; ſo having furnisht it with proviſions, as well as that short time would give them leave, His <hi>Ex<hi rend="sup">cy</hi>.</hi> commits the charge of that
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:118090:12"/> place to <hi>S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Arthur Aſton,</hi> as a perſon whoſe experience, courage, &amp; approued fidelity did worthily deſerve the higheſt truſt. Theſe things thus ordered His <hi>Ex<hi rend="sup">cy</hi>.</hi> returnes to <hi>Trim,</hi> and from thence he diſpatched away <hi>Co<hi rend="sup">ll</hi>. Daniell O Neale</hi> then Governor of that place, (with a Commiſſion to ſet on foot the <hi>treaty</hi> againe with <hi>Owen O Neale,</hi> if it were poſſible, &amp; to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour the reduceing of the <hi>Vlſter</hi> army even upon any condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions;) a perſon eſteemed by all, beſt qualified for that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, as well in regard of his ſingular abillitye, and approued fidelitie to the <hi>King</hi> as the great intereſt he was ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to have in his Unckle, who managed the buſines with that dexteritye, as he won his Unckle to harken againe, unto an agreement; wherupon. <hi>S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Richard Barnewell,</hi> and <hi>S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Nicholas Plunkett</hi> are ſent after to make an abſolute concluſion with him, though by the way this may not be unworthy of obſervation, that thoſe perſons who were formerly moſt oppoſit to this agreement, were now become the greateſt ſticklers to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote it with His <hi>Ex<hi rend="sup">cy</hi>,</hi> being growne ſencible of the immi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, and aproaching danger that now threatned them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tecroghan</hi> is the next ſtage His <hi>Ex<hi rend="sup">cy</hi>.</hi> removes unto, (where I had the honor firſt to kiſſe his hand after my arrivall in <hi>Ireland,)</hi> here he makes a ſtand, as being the moſt opportune place to draw his army together in, and lyeing moſt convenient after that was don, to releive <hi>Drogheda,</hi> or make any other attempt upon the enemy: Where beſids the remains of the <hi>Irish</hi> army, already ſom what recruited, there joyned unto him a good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment of my Lord <hi>Marqueſs</hi> of <hi>Clanricards</hi> of above 1000 foot, together vvith 300 horſe; likevviſe that party of the <hi>Scots</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mentioned; <hi>S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Thomas Armſtrong,</hi> and <hi>Co<hi rend="sup">ll</hi>. Treuors,</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether vvith vvhat forces my Lord <hi>Inchiquin</hi> could bring out of
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:118090:13"/> his precincts; theſe being got together, and daily additions being ſtill expected to the making them up a more conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable body, then they were at <hi>Dublin;</hi> my <hi>Lord Leiu<hi rend="sup">t</hi>.</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaved ſeverall advices from <hi>S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Arthur Aſton</hi> to precipitate nothing: for he doubted not of finding <hi>Cromwell</hi> play a while, as certainly he had done had not <hi>Co<hi rend="sup">ll</hi>. Walls</hi> regiment after the enemy had bin twice bravely repulſed; upon the unfortunat loſſe of their Collonell in the third aſſault bin ſo unhappily dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maide, as to liſten before they had neede unto the enemy of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering them quarter; and admitted them in upon theſe termes; therby betraying both themſelves, &amp; all their fellow ſouldiers to the ſlaughter; for <hi>Cromwell</hi> being maſter of the towne, &amp; told by <hi>Jones</hi> that he had now in his hands the flower of the <hi>Irish</hi> ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, gave order to have all that were in armes put to the ſword: Where beſides the gallant Governour <hi>S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Arthur Aſton, S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Edmond Varney, Co<hi rend="sup">ll</hi>. Warren, Co<hi rend="sup">ll</hi>. Fleminge,</hi> and <hi>Co<hi rend="sup">ll</hi>. Birn, Leiu<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Co<hi rend="sup">ll</hi>. Finglaſſe,</hi> and <hi>Major Tempeſt,</hi> together with many other excellent Officers, and Gentlemen, there were butchered neare 3000 ſouldiers, and thoſe truly reputed the beſt that <hi>Kingdom</hi> affoorded: in whoſe fall, there is ſadly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervable, how great a number of them were guilty of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lucky breach of that ſolemne agreement, made about two yeares before betweene the Lord <hi>Marqueſſe</hi> of <hi>Clanricard</hi> and the <hi>Leinſter</hi> army at <hi>S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Nicholas Whites Caſtle</hi> of <hi>Lexleap;</hi> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall of thoſe that ſurvived having perisht ſince; and few, or none of them eſcaped ſome remarkable affliction, or other. This maſſacre at <hi>Drogheda</hi> having lopt of a principall limbe of my <hi>Lord Leiu<hi rend="sup">ts</hi>.</hi> army; and the loſſe of that towne, letting the enemy looſe, cauſed his <hi>Ex<hi rend="sup">cy</hi>
               </hi> to remove his army from <hi>Caſtle Jordan</hi> down towards the Counties of <hi>Wexford,</hi> and <hi>Kilkeny,</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:118090:13"/> there not only to lye ſecure, till Generall <hi>O Neales</hi> army came up unto them (with whom now at laſt he having bin rejected by the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and the <hi>Commiſsioners</hi> whipt to reaſon with ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity, there was an agreement made, and he ſubmitted to the Kings Authority) but alſo ready to be drawne into either <hi>Wex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> or <hi>Kilkeny,</hi> as there should be occaſion, for upon one of thoſe places after the enemies retreat from <hi>Drogheda</hi> to <hi>Dublin,</hi> it was concluded they would fall next. For which reaſon His <hi>Ex<hi rend="sup">cy</hi>.</hi> for many daies courts the towne of <hi>Wexford</hi> to take in a Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon, <hi>Kilkeny</hi> having received one already, but they (affirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they were able to defend their towne themſelves) would never be brought to admit of one till the enemy was at the Walls, and then tumultuarily <hi>S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Edmond Butler</hi> with neare 1500 men was receaved in, as Governour; whome to rein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force, after the enemy was now ſet down before it my <hi>Lord Leiu<hi rend="sup">nt</hi>
               </hi> comes with new ſupplies with in ſight of the towne, &amp; had put them in, to the infallible preſervation of the place, if <hi>James Stafford</hi> then Governour of the Caſtle had not upon termes of advantage to himſelfe before His <hi>Ex<hi rend="sup">cies</hi>
               </hi> eies shamefully be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed it, and the town into the hands of a moſt cruell, &amp; faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe <hi>enemy,</hi> who butchered there alſo after they were admitted in, above 2000 more.</p>
            <p>There was nothing now remainning to be done, the <hi>Vlſter</hi> army being not yet come up, and ſeverall troopes of my Lord <hi>Inchiquins</hi> being ſince the ſeidge of <hi>Drogheda</hi> run away to the enemy) but put a Garriſon into <hi>Roſſe</hi> which was ſent in under the Command of <hi>Luke Taaffe</hi> with orders (for the place was judged ſcarce tenable againſt ſo powerfull an enemy) to make conditions when they ſaw themſelves able to reſiſt no longer, as at laſt they did when the breach was made, and the enemy
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:118090:14"/> ready to give an aſſault, haveing termes to march away with their armes.</p>
            <p>About <hi>Graigge</hi> and <hi>Thomas Town</hi> His <hi>Excellency</hi> houered with his horſe, and the ſmall remainder of his foot, untill the come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up of the <hi>Vlſter</hi> army. Vnder the Command of <hi>Leiutenant Generall Farrell,</hi> (the <hi>Generall</hi> himſelfe lying then a dying:) This new Conjunction with <hi>Owen O Neale,</hi> and ſo great an acceſſion of Forces bringes my <hi>Lord Leiutenant</hi> into a Condition not only of putting a ſtop upon <hi>Cromwells</hi> haſty progreſſe, but even of gaining ground upon him, as queſtionleſſe he would have done, had not another misfortune greater then any of the former interveened to fruſtrate all; which was this, my Lord of <hi>Inchequin</hi> having as I ſaid before conditioned to have the order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of thoſe Garriſons, and forces that he brought in with him to the <hi>Kings</hi> obedience left wholy to himſelfe out of deſire (as is beleeved) to keep himſelfe ſtill conſiderable upon a bottome of his owne; would never hearken unto any Propoſition of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting a proportion of <hi>Irish</hi> into any of his townes, King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſale onely excepted into which place at the importunity of <hi>Prince Rupert</hi> he at laſt admitted ſome: Being confident that the <hi>English</hi> forces under his command having ſerved under him ſo ſo long upon ſeverall ſcores; all, or the moſt of the Officers where of being either Creatures of his owne, or men obliged, and indeared unto him upon a long account, would never ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate themſelves from his fortune, or abandon his ſervice. But his <hi>Lordship</hi> it ſeemes tooke wrong meaſures, for the moſt part of them being ſteared wholy by ſelfe intereſt, and knowing the way already, how for advantage to ſerve againſt the <hi>King</hi> (whoſe buſineſs they ſaw ſo much declining, that no more was likely to be got that way) whilſt <hi>Cromwell</hi> was full of mony,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:118090:14"/> and ſucceſſe; Conſpired together how to poſſeſs themſelves of my Lord of <hi>Inchiquins</hi> perſon, together with the townes under his Command, that they might make a ſurrender of all at once unto the enemy: <hi>Youghall</hi> begins the dance, and taking occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to mutiny againſt the <hi>English Cavaliers</hi> under <hi>Woogans</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand that were quartered there, impriſoned, &amp; diſarmd them all, and afterwards ſtood upon their guard.</p>
            <p>Whilſt my Lord of <hi>Iuchiquin</hi> is by all Gentle meanes en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring to reclayme back this towne, ſeverall of his Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers combine to ſeize upon him, (then lying ſecure at <hi>Leiute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant Generall Barries</hi> houſe of <hi>Caſtle Lyons)</hi> but they, and their deſigne being diſcovered to his Lordship by one of their owne complices, were ſo farr prevented as to be ſeized all upon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. Wherupon the towne of <hi>Youghall</hi> ſeing <hi>Cromwell</hi> yet at too great a diſtance, &amp; the time of his coming into <hi>Mounſter</hi> uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, offered to ſubmit upon aſſurance of <hi>indemnity,</hi> the releaſe of the <hi>impriſoned Officers,</hi> and removall of the <hi>Cavaliers;</hi> which his Lordship either wanting the meanes to compell them, or being willing with kindneſſe, and faire meanes to vvin upon them, &amp; keep them in order aſſented unto. After which, having viſited his Garriſons, and beleeving all things ſo ſecure, as not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire either his further ſtay there, or the bringing any propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Irish</hi> into thoſe other townes, he returnes unto his charge in the army. And novv <hi>Cromwell</hi> having nevvly received an affront before <hi>Duncannon,</hi> through the courage &amp; gallantry of <hi>Wogan</hi> vvirh thoſe <hi>English</hi> Gentlemen, that vvere put in vvith him upon that occaſion, vvas retired back to <hi>Roſſe</hi> there under the Protection of the town to make a <hi>Floting Bridge</hi> over the river to the end that by having a paſſage to the other ſide, he might at his pleaſure either compell His <hi>Ex<hi rend="sup">cy</hi>
               </hi> to devide his army, to
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:118090:15"/> attend upon his motions and ſo give him an opportunity of ſetting upon one part, or other of it; Or, at leaſt, if it kept to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, of getting a Paſſage into <hi>Mounſter,</hi> where he expected, to find a generall Revolt of thoſe Garriſons under my Lord of <hi>Inchiquins</hi> Commands, as it afterwards happened.</p>
            <p>My Lord <hi>Taaffe</hi> was ſent with a part of the army to hinder the worke; But what through want of powder, (and indeed all ſortes of ammunition) which was now grown exceeding ſcarce, extremity of foule weather, diſtempers amongſt his men, and other ill concurring accidents, he was not able to effect it. My <hi>Lord Leiutenant</hi> through <hi>Cromwells</hi> ſuddain retreating in the night, from before <hi>Dun Cannon,</hi> having loſt the oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity of fighting him, (as he was then reſolved finding his army cherfully deſire the occaſion) had nothing left him now to do, but vvaite upon the enemies motion, and endeavour to cut of his proviſions, (vvhich the country people allured by the orderlineſſe of his ſouldiers, who had mony to pay for vvhat they tooke, and command it ſeemes to do ſo) brought them in as faſt as could be; vvhilſt His <hi>Excellency</hi> having no mony to pay his army, nor indeed a competence of bread to give them, vvas conſtrained to let them take their ſuſtenance vvhere they could find it.</p>
            <p>During this intermiſſion of action, <hi>Corke, Youghall,</hi> and all the <hi>English</hi> townes of <hi>Mounſter</hi> (even through the incitation of thoſe Officers, that were but lately releaſed) being openly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volted, and the Lord <hi>Broghall</hi> with ſome men landed in thoſe parts; Very many of my Lord <hi>Inchiquins</hi> party, both horſe, and foote deſerted my <hi>Lord Leiutenant,</hi> and ran daily over to the enemy: In ſo much that both the Commanders, and ſouldiers of the <hi>Irish</hi> (not without reaſon) grew very jealous of the reſt
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:118090:15"/> that remained behind, fearing that if ever they came to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage againſt the enemy, they would turne upon them, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray them, there wanted not diverſe alſo (though doubtleſs very unjuſtly) that extended their jealouſies unto my Lord of <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiquin</hi> himſelfe grounding their accuſations upon his <hi>Lordships</hi> not punishing the <hi>Conſpirators</hi> when he had them in his power, upon ſo faire a warning, and juſt an occaſion, as then was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him, his not putting <hi>Irish</hi> into his Garriſons; Upon his wife, his family, plate, and goods being ſent him ſafely out of <hi>Corke</hi> into the <hi>Irish</hi> quartars, upon his not conſenting to the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounting, and diſarming, of the reſt of his men, when ſome of the <hi>Commiſsioners</hi> preſt the doing of it, upon his delivering his advice in <hi>Councell</hi> (as they heard for his <hi>Excellencies</hi> coming to conditions with <hi>Cromwell,</hi> and making this an argument for it, that his men would fight no longer; and laſtly upon an imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent accuſation without head, or taile (appeared when he came to be examined in the buſineſſe) brought againſt him by the Marques of <hi>Antrim,</hi> for holding correſpondence, and having made conditions under hand with the enemy.</p>
            <p>Upon theſe foundations, and ſuch as theſe, did many of the <hi>Irish</hi> repreſent unto my <hi>Lord Leiutenant</hi> the neceſſity of diſcharg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my Lord <hi>Inchiquin</hi> of his Command, &amp; ſecuring his perſon; which his <hi>Excellency</hi> being more tender of the Kings honour, and his owne, then upon bare ſurmiſes, and ſuſpitions to deale in that manner with a perſon that had but lately <hi>deſerved ſo well</hi> both of the <hi>King,</hi> and <hi>him;</hi> would not be brought unto: Choos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing rather to run any adventure, then to be guilty of breach of conditions with him, which he muſt needs have been, if before a conviction of apparent treachery he should upon the ſcore of my Lord of <hi>Inchiquins</hi> overſights, or the uncertain jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:118090:16"/> of the <hi>Irish;</hi> have condeſcended unto either of the things propoſed.</p>
            <p>This temper and juſtice in my <hi>Lord Leiutenant</hi> (in not ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelfe to be led by the clamors and importunity of the people, and ſoldiers) involues him alſo at laſt under their diſpleaſure, and miſtruſt: ſo that out of want of confidence in their cheife Commanders, and out of diffidence in one another, the army was now falln into a very unfit condition of hazarding a battaile with the enemy, if an occaſion should offer it ſelfe: and to make it worſe the <hi>Scots</hi> that were there (being tired out with the neceſſities, the whole army ſuffered, and receiving newes of the enemies prevalence in their Country) deſired leave to returne into the North which after great importunity at laſt being granted them, they immediately with drew their forces, and haſted homewards; where they were no ſooner come, and <hi>S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. George Monro</hi> joynd unto them, but they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived ſo ſore a blow from <hi>Coote</hi> with ſo much loſſe, and diſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of their men that they were never able to make head in <hi>Vlſter</hi> ſince.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cromwell</hi> now finding the army ſo much weakened, by the deſertion of ſo many of my Lord <hi>Inchiquins</hi> men, and the depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the <hi>Scots,</hi> and likewiſe knowing that it was in ſuch diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der through the diſtruſt, &amp; animoſities that were amongſt them, ſo that in reaſon he was like to have much the advantage if they should fight him, adventures over his bridge at <hi>Roſſe</hi> into the County of <hi>Kilkenny;</hi> where by facing my Lord <hi>Leiutenants</hi> army, and mouing after it up, and down, he amuzed the <hi>Irish;</hi> whilſt <hi>Jones,</hi> his <hi>Leintenant Generall,</hi> with parties tooke in the Caſtles of the Country, &amp; had <hi>Carrick</hi> given into his hands wretchedly by <hi>Martin</hi> that Commanded there; Upon notice where of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:118090:16"/> 
               <hi>Cromwell</hi> haſtens thither, to paſſe his army over into <hi>Mounſter,</hi> which was now his buſineſs; for notwithſtanding his purſe to buy proviſions of the Country, and his ships that wherever he went waited continually upon him, his army through the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſonableneſſe of the weather, and want of quarters, was ſo much haraſſed, and waſted; many of his men falling ſick, and dying daily, that if he did not haſten to his Winter quarters, he would in probability have perished without a blow, which ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſſe, to make ſure worke, my <hi>Lord Leiutenant</hi> (whoſe army alſo was quite tired out with wants, ſufferings, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall marches) hearing that he was gone towards <hi>Carrick</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to beſtow upon him before neceſſity forced him to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſe his men, and to that end his <hi>Excellency</hi> marcht ſpeedily af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the enemy with deſigne to ſet upon him whilſt he was either engaged before <hi>Carrick,</hi> or elſe incumbred at ſome other paſſe upon the river; but after all this diligence when my <hi>Lord</hi> came near the towne he then learnt that the place was loſt before, and that <hi>Cromwell</hi> leaving a competent Garriſon therin, had only paſt his army over, and was gone towards <hi>Waterford,</hi> which town during <hi>Cromwells</hi> Reſidence at <hi>Roſſe,</hi> though the perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion (as it is ſaid) of <hi>Geoffry Baron,</hi> and <hi>Hugh Rochford</hi> had un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derhand begun a treaty with him, for the delivery of the town unto him; Which treaty only ſtuck upon the free exerciſe of their Religion, and the Churches denyed unto them by <hi>Cromwell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The knowledge of this cauſed my <hi>Lord Leiutenant</hi> now to haſten thither, with no ſmall danger to his perſon to preſſe them to admit of a Garriſon, which being a long time denyed, &amp; my Lord of <hi>Caſtlehaven,</hi> with diverſe others, that his <hi>Excellency</hi> propounded, being utterly rejected by them; yet at laſt they
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:118090:17"/> were content to admit of <hi>Farrell,</hi> and the <hi>Vlſter</hi> men, who ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly were ſent immediately unto them. After <hi>Farrells</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittance, he upon notice of the enemies motion that way, fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſome commotion in the towne, and thinking himſelfe not ſtrong enough to reſiſt the enemy without, and maſter them within writes unto his <hi>Excellency</hi> for a ſupply of men; And theſe his <hi>Excellency</hi> (ſeing <hi>Cromwell</hi> ſo unexpectedly got over into <hi>Mounſter</hi> through the treachery of the Garriſon of <hi>Carrick)</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends now to conduct himſelfe out of hand into <hi>Waterford,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore which the enemy was ſuppoſed to bee; Therupon ſome Principall Officers of the army deſired leave that they might in the Interim attempt the regaining of <hi>Carrick,</hi> againſt whom his <hi>Excellency</hi> objecting the want of materialls neceſſary for ſuch an enterprize, was aſſured they had enough to ſerve their turne for that worke, yea, and ſome of them poſitively under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tooke the taking of the place that night; Wherfore leaving them to their buſineſſe my <hi>Lord</hi> bends his Courſe for <hi>Water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> where he arrived when it was late; upon notice where of <hi>Cromwell</hi> deſpairing of doing any good upon that town, and finding many of his men fall ſick, and dy of the fluxe, which then raged amongſt them, drawes of in the night, and haſtens towards his Winter quarters at <hi>Corke</hi> and <hi>Youghall,</hi> in which march as he gaind <hi>Dungarvan,</hi> ſo he loſt <hi>Jones</hi> his Leiutenant Generall.</p>
            <p>During my <hi>Lord Leiutenants</hi> abſence, the army at <hi>Carrick</hi> aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaults the place, the foot falling on with extraordinary galan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and reſolution, where after the loſſe of many of them, they faild of carrying the place only for want of a few pickaxes, and ſpades which being calld for were no where to be found, which neceſſitated the poore foot, after having done ſo hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomely,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:118090:17"/> and ſtood under the walls ſome houres, to quit the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs, and draw of; when extreame want of food (they having eaten nothing almoſt for two daies) enforced them to march away towards <hi>Clonmell,</hi> all the Country betvixt <hi>Carrick,</hi> and <hi>Kilkenny</hi> Being totally ſpoild already.</p>
            <p>The remouall of the army hence without ſending notice of it to my <hi>Lord Leiutenant</hi> had like to have put his <hi>Excellency</hi> into the enemies hands, for he making full account of the regaining of <hi>Carrick</hi> upon the former aſſurance that was given him, was upon his way directly thither, (where the enemy had 300 horſe, &amp; he not forty in his Company) when Colonell <hi>Milo Power</hi> by good fortune found him out, and told him of the ill ſucceſs of the enterprize, and the motion of the army thence, wherupon he altered his Courſe another way. And then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering that the enemy was now retired into his Garriſons, that the weather was bitter, and unfit for action, the Winter being now come on, or if it were not ſo that he had neither meat, nor mony wherwith to keep his men any longer toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, having ſince the revolt of <hi>Mounſter</hi> (which deprived him of the greateſt share of his Contributions, and Proviſions) been along time already forced to live upon the ſpoile of the reſt of the Country; he concluded upon diſperſing his army into quarters alſo, which (becauſe the Principall townes refuſed to admit them in) he was fain to ſcatter over all the Kingdom. The greateſt part of the <hi>Vlſter</hi> forces were ſent into their own Province there to Chooſe a new <hi>Generall</hi> according as their conditions allowed them. <hi>Luke Taaffe,</hi> and <hi>Morogh, O Flahartye</hi> with their men were ſent back into <hi>Connaght</hi> to my Lord of <hi>Clanricard;</hi> my Lord of <hi>Inchiquin</hi> with the remainder of ſuch as belonged unto him, went over into the County of <hi>Clare;</hi> my
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:118090:18"/> Lord <hi>Dillon</hi> with his, into <hi>Meath,</hi> and towards <hi>Athlone,</hi> all the reſt were ſcattered ſeverall wayes; Only Major Generall <hi>Hugh O Neale</hi> was admitted with about 1500 <hi>Vlſter</hi> men into <hi>Clonmell</hi> as Governour, and <hi>Kilkenny</hi> received alſo a Competent Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon to ſecure them againſt ſo ill neighbours as <hi>Roſſe,</hi> and <hi>Carrick</hi> were.</p>
            <p>Here your Lordship beholds a ſummary of what paſt in the feild, ſince the army firſt ſet forth untill their going to their Winter quarters; in all which time how ill ſoever the ſucceſſe hath been, nothing can with any colour of reaſon be laid to my <hi>Lord Leiutenants</hi> charge, except the not punishing thoſe many <hi>failings, treacheries,</hi> and <hi>diſorders</hi> that were committed during this Summers expedition: Yet as to the diſobedience, &amp; neglects in the ſeidge of <hi>Dublin</hi> I gave you reaſons why that was paſt over before; And thoſe that were committed ſince were for the moſt part by men of that condition, &amp; Intereſt, that it was neither ſafe, nor fit (all things conſidered) to call them to an account; as for treacheries, moſt of the authors of them tooke care to ſecure themſelves and in time get out of reach; Only <hi>Crosby</hi> that betraid <hi>Kingſale,</hi> after he was deſigned to dy, by my <hi>Lord Leiutenant,</hi> upon my Lord of <hi>Inchiquins</hi> coming to towne, was, I know not for what conſiderations, repreived and ſaved; The want of mony to pay the ſoldiers, and the exigences they were for the moſt part in, after the miſchance at <hi>Dublin,</hi> did ſo much authorize their diſorders in the Country that if they had not been paſt by, and connived at, there had been no meanes of keeping them together. There was no Officer in all that army, that will not likewiſe confeſſe that my Lord of <hi>Ormond</hi> did too often, and too freely expoſe himſelfe to danger by going upon every litle expedition; and that he did take more
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:118090:18"/> toile, and paines then became a <hi>Generall,</hi> by deſcending fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently to play the <hi>Major Generall,</hi> the <hi>Quarter-Maſter,</hi> the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voſt Marshall,</hi> or any thing; which yet the unremediable negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, and inſufficiency of many of his Officers obliged him unto.</p>
            <p>Out of all which it is very evident that it was neither want of conduct, courage, or vigilancy in <hi>him</hi> that brought thoſe ſad ſucceſſes upon the <hi>Irish,</hi> but (next after the immediate hand of God) thoſe <hi>factions,</hi> that hee had neither power, nor meanes of maſtering, thoſe <hi>treacheries,</hi> which no mans Prudence could prevent, and thoſe <hi>wants,</hi> that his empty purſe and deep en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged fortune could not ſupply. For I dare boldy ſay, that had it not been for the averſion of the Commiſſioners, my Lord of <hi>Caſtlehaven,</hi> my Lord of <hi>Inchiquin,</hi> &amp; the <hi>Scots,</hi> to <hi>Owen O Neale,</hi> he had been reduced in time; Both <hi>Derry,</hi> and <hi>Dublin</hi> would have fallen into my <hi>Lord Leiuteuants</hi> hands, &amp; no landing place have been left for <hi>Cromwell</hi> unſecured: Nay, I have many reaſons to beleeve, that notwithſtanding the defeat at <hi>Dublin,</hi> and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe upon <hi>Drogheda, Cromwell</hi> with all his great army, his fleet, and ſtore of mony, had been loſt, and ſunke to nothing, if the Caſtles of <hi>Wexford,</hi> and <hi>Carrick</hi> had not been ſo fowly betrayed; Nay, and after that too, if thoſe townes, and forces in <hi>Mounſter</hi> had not ſo treacherouſly revolted.</p>
            <p>But how innocent ſoever his <hi>Excellency</hi> were, by this time, ſome leaders of the <hi>factious</hi> part of the <hi>Cleargy,</hi> and people (thinking now they had got a faire occaſion of lifting him out of the ſaddle, and therby of ſlipping their own necks out of the collar of obedience again,) begin to exclaime aloud againſt my <hi>Lord Leiutenant</hi> for their ill ſucceſſes; they blame his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of the army, as if he had miſguided it on purpoſe; his
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:118090:19"/> diſpoſing of their contributions, as if he had defrauded them; his Kindneſſe, &amp; Countenance to the <hi>English</hi> Gentlemen, was a ſigne he wisht our Nation, better then his owne; and an infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of his not being fit to be truſted longer by them; for to confirme which they coined a thouſand arguments, and ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered induſtriouſly amongſt the people opinions, that my Lord of <hi>Ormond</hi> was guilty of the greateſt treacheries, and miſcarriages that had been committed. To make which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, they called to mind afresh the ſurrender of <hi>Dublin</hi> to the <hi>Parliament,</hi> rather then to <hi>them,</hi> They inſtanced alſo his preſent ſupporting my Lord of <hi>Inchiquin,</hi> though ſuſpected ſo deeply by every one; Nay, out of his ſtanding ſo hard with them in all paſt <hi>treaties</hi> upon conceſſions of Religion, and out of his ſteadineſſe in his own Profeſſion, they framed arguments of his unfaithfullneſs to them, and averſion to theirs: So that now you could ſpeake with few amongſt the common ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, or the peaſants that would not either ſay, they could not looke to proſper under the Command of a <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> or elſe tell you, that it was no wonder their armies were beaten, and their townes were loſt, ſince their cheife leaders betraid them.</p>
            <p>Thus did the knavery, and malice of a few ſteale away the hearts of the generallity of that undiſcerning ſimple people from my <hi>Lord Leiutenant,</hi> few of them being able to judge at all of the Prudence and integrity of his conduct; or to conſider that the army that was in the feild the foregoing Summer would have required foure times the Contribution that was raiſed, without leaving any ſurplus either to be hoarded up, or ſent beyond ſeas: From which his <hi>Excellency</hi> was ſo farr, that on the other ſide, he frequently offered to engage at a very
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:118090:19"/> low rate all that remained unmorgaged of his Princely eſtate for the ſupport of the army.</p>
            <p>Theſe people could not reflect how much right, and honour he did their Nation in his Civillities, &amp; Nobleneſſe to thoſe <hi>English Gentlemen,</hi> that were in want, and Bannishment only for their faith unto the <hi>King,</hi> and who, if ever the <hi>Royall Intereſt</hi> recovered, were many of them like to become ſo capeable of acknowledging thoſe favours with advantages back unto them; wherfore his <hi>Excellency,</hi> as well out of their common con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernments, as his own goodneſſe, bewayled nothing more, then that his own private, and the Kingdomes publique neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities limitted his bounty; and that the ill nature, and indiſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that raigned amongſt many of the <hi>Irish</hi> would not ſuffer them to hide their repininges, at his favour towards theſe Gentlemen.</p>
            <p>The ſurrender of <hi>Dublin</hi> truly had been made unto the people of <hi>Ireland</hi> by the arts of thoſe, that were at that time in Government amongſt them, a moſt odious thing; though thoſe very perſons knew well enough, it was themſelves and not my <hi>Lord Leiutenant,</hi> that was in the fault; by twice fowly violating their <hi>publique faith</hi> with him, firſt in breaking a <hi>peace</hi> made, and ſolemnly published both at <hi>Dublin,</hi> and <hi>Kilkenny,</hi> (the reſpective ſeates of the <hi>Kings Leiutenant</hi> and the <hi>Councell</hi> of the <hi>Confederates)</hi> &amp; in ſeconding that act (after having impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned the <hi>Lord Muskerij, S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Robert Talbott, S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Lucas Dillon, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Brown, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Belings,</hi> and the reſt of their <hi>Supream Councell,</hi> that had made the peace, and ſtill ſtood honeſtly to what they had done) with bringing their armies before <hi>Dublin,</hi> where having cauſed the burning, and deſtruction of thoſe quarters, the town it ſelfe muſt have been loſt unto them, if upon over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:118090:20"/> of a treaty with the <hi>Parliament</hi> they had not ſent men and ſupplies to reſcue it. And next in the breach of that ſolemn <hi>engagement</hi> made between them, and the Marqueſs of <hi>Clanricard,</hi> as ſoone as (upon beleife of their reſolution to return unto their duty) the treaty was broke of, and the forces of the <hi>Parliament</hi> ſent home again; Could it be expected, that after two ſuch acts as theſe any wiſe man would truſt, or treat with the <hi>Irish</hi> any more, whilſt the Government was ſtill in the ſame mens hands; Who after all this wrought the whole <hi>Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly</hi> to declare they would never have any <hi>Proteſtant Governour</hi> more, and namely not my Lord <hi>Leiutenant;</hi> and who were not ashamed at the ſame time, both to anull the <hi>Peace,</hi> and yet acknowledge that the forementiond <hi>Gentlemen</hi> that had been makers of it, and ſuffered in juſtification of it, had neither ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded their inſtructions, nor done any thing misbecoming honeſt men.</p>
            <p>Theſe kind of proceedings at <hi>Kilkenny</hi> joynd to a new expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition deſigned againſt <hi>Dublin,</hi> as ſoon as the ſeaſon of the yeare would ſuffer them to march, were, it muſt needs bee Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed Provocations ſufficient to have juſtified my Lord <hi>Leiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant</hi> (if he had received no ſuch inſtructions from the <hi>King</hi> as he did) finding himſelf unable to keep the place any longer, in the ſurrender of it: (rather then to ſo faithleſſe a people, as thoſe were, that then ſwaied there, and who were driving on a forraign Intereſts with might and main) into the hands of the <hi>Parliament</hi> (who were at that time in treaty with the <hi>King)</hi> upon conditions of giving him free acceſſe to <hi>His</hi> MAjESTY, and of repaying unto him thoſe monies, which hee during the troubles of his Government (the <hi>Kings Exchequer</hi> failing) had out of his own purſe lent unto the army. Whether His <hi>Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency</hi>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:118090:20"/> did in this caſe like a man of honour, and as became him, let the late Generall <hi>O Neale</hi> be judge, who (if he be not much wrongd) did affirme unto a confident freind of his, that if he had been intruſted from the <hi>English</hi> Nation, and with the Intereſts of the <hi>Crown of England</hi> there, as my <hi>Lord Leiutenant</hi> was, he would have done juſt ſo, as His <hi>Excellency</hi> then did.</p>
            <p>His ſupporting my Lord <hi>Inchiquin</hi> then ſinking in the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall opinion, if it had been duly waighd, should have been an argument of much comfort, and ſatisfaction to this <hi>jealous people</hi> to ſee his <hi>Excellency</hi> ſo tender of the <hi>Kings</hi> honour, and his own word; ſo juſt in his freindships, and ſo exactly carefull to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve conditions; Out of his warineſs in all his treaties with them, they might alſo have pleaſed to infer (rather, then what they did) theſe two things; firſt that like a faithfull ſervant, he endeavoured to make as good a bargain as he could for the <hi>King</hi> his maſter; &amp; ſecondly that without deſignes of cheating them into their duty (like thoſe, that ſome others had) he was reſolud to aſſent unto nothing, but what His MAjESTY, and <hi>he</hi> might juſtly own, and ſafely make good unto them: Finally his ſteadineſſe in a religion, that from very tender yeares he had been imbued with, and his firmneſſe in his loialty, in having ſtood for many yeares all thoſe batteries, that either with ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments or incredible offers of advantage, they had often made to win him to their party; in ſo much, that they might ſee that nothing but the hand of <hi>God</hi> and the convinceing of his judgement could alter him in the firſt, nor any thing in the world corrupt, or shake him in the latter, might at leaſt have been an aſſurance to them, that he would never become a <hi>Proſelite</hi> to a Religion far leſſe rationall, and alluring, then theirs was (I mean <hi>Independancy)</hi> and that having refuſed to become their
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:118090:21"/> 
               <hi>Prince,</hi> he would not betray ſo eminent a loyalty, his Country, his freinds, and ſo noble a fortune as his is, only to become a <hi>Vaſſall</hi> unto <hi>Cromwell;</hi> from whom he could not poſſibly promiſe to himſelfe (if a ſecurity for the performance, or permanence of it could be given him) any thing of honour, or advantage equall to what he did already enioy, and might hereafter juſtly promiſe to himſelfe from the <hi>King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus went thoſe kind of <hi>Spiders</hi> about making poiſon out of every thing, where with having now either allienated, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected farr the greater part of the Kingdom, by abuſing them at home, they have attempted alſo to do the ſame abroad, and moſt particularly at <hi>Court,</hi> by their letters, and ſneaking <hi>emiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries</hi> ſuch as <hi>Hugh Rochford</hi> and <hi>Fitzmorris,</hi> who, under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of great devotion to the <hi>King,</hi> by impudent corner <hi>ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtions,</hi> and malicious <hi>whiſpers,</hi> have laid all the foregoing ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſations to His <hi>Excellencyes</hi> Charge, &amp; endeavoured ſo to blaſt him there, that his MAjESTY might have been enduced to remove him from the Government, which on my ſoule if he had done, or should do, whilſt theſe <hi>diſtractions</hi> continue, it were the ready way to ruine all his Intereſts in that Kingdom; for my Lord of <hi>Clanricard</hi> wauing it, as (eſpecially upon that ſcore, and ſuch a conjuncture) without doubt he would have done, <hi>Irland</hi> afforded not another perſon, who for all reſpects was able, and fit for that truſt; and no <hi>ſtranger</hi> could have been ſent, whoſe want of knowledge in that Nation, and want of intereſt amongſt them, should not have laid him open to ſo great diſadvantages, as he should have done nothing elſe but looſe himſelfe, and the <hi>Kings</hi> buſineſſe. Which is the Reall end, which theſe baſe informers, and their abettors driue at, and the lurch they ly at for the broaching of a new Rebellion;
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:118090:21"/> the impoſſibility of ſetting which on foot, whilſt ſo wiſe, and experienced a perſon, and one of ſo great an alliance, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in the Kingdom is at the helme: and their utter deſpaire of ever being able to bring my Lord of <hi>Ormond</hi> to their bent, are the only true reaſons of all their perſecutions of, and aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions to him.</p>
            <p>Whom, as I remember, (before this long, yet neceſſary digreſſion) I left at <hi>Kilkenny,</hi> where having in vain endeavoured to qualify the univerſall diſcontents, and obſerving how faſt (notwithſtanding the admonitory Declaration of all the <hi>Bishops</hi> from <hi>Clonmaenoſſe</hi> to the contrary) the people being alienated with the rauaging, and diſorder of their own armies, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lured with the ſucceſſes, and ſmooth invitations of <hi>Cromwell,</hi> ran headlong into him for Protection, and vnder Contribution; as alſo, how great numbers of the <hi>Irish</hi> ſouldiers, ſome frighted with the <hi>plague,</hi> which now began to ſpread into the other Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces of the Kingdom, and others for want of livelyhood, as having neither meat, nor pay, flockt in unto the enemy. He goes into <hi>Conaght</hi> to confer about carrying on of the publicke buſineſſe, and the remedy of theſe diſorders with the Marquis of <hi>Clanricarde</hi> at his Caſtle of <hi>Portumna</hi> about the end of Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas; who being a perſon of that eminent merit towards our <hi>King,</hi> and <hi>Nation,</hi> &amp; deſerving ſo much honour from all honeſt men; I shall, I beleive, do a thing very pleaſing to your <hi>Lordship</hi> to give you a breife Character of him.</p>
            <p>The Story of his <hi>Charity,</hi> and <hi>Protection</hi> to ſuch multitudes of diſtreſst <hi>English,</hi> and <hi>Proteſtants</hi> in the time of thoſe <hi>Tragicall Maſſacres,</hi> and <hi>Rapines,</hi> that at the beginning of the warr were acted in <hi>Irland;</hi> &amp; his <hi>Civillities,</hi> &amp; <hi>Nobleneſſe</hi> to thoſe of our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, whoſe honeſty deſerved his favour ever ſince hath ſo many
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:118090:22"/> 
               <hi>Liveing Relators,</hi> that I need not medle with it; likewiſe for me to give a particular account with what <hi>integrity,</hi> and <hi>wiſdome</hi> he hath preſervd his <hi>Loyalty,</hi> through all thoſe <hi>ſtraits,</hi> &amp; <hi>troubles</hi> that have hedgd him in, free from the guilt of the leaſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance with either the <hi>Parliament,</hi> or <hi>Confederates,</hi> though me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naced, and courted incredibly by all, not only the <hi>Nuntio</hi> and <hi>O Neale,</hi> but even by <hi>Sultan Cromwell</hi> himſelfe (as looking upon his <hi>Lordship</hi> for the perſon likelieſt now to give him the greateſt oppoſition, and to contribute moſt to the preſervation of what was left) all which aſſaults he hath ſtood out with the greateſt <hi>conſtancy,</hi> and <hi>modeſty</hi> in the world, would make me too tedious upon this occaſion.</p>
            <p>Wherfore I shall content my ſelfe to tell your Lordship in short, that he hath conducted his own, and that share he hath had of the <hi>Kings</hi> buſineſſe, with the greateſt <hi>prudence,</hi> &amp; <hi>honeſty</hi> the freeſt from <hi>faction,</hi> or <hi>ambition,</hi> and with the cleareſt neglect of <hi>ſelfe intereſt,</hi> &amp; <hi>private advantages,</hi> that hath ever yet falln under my obſervation; in fine I will aſſure you, he is a <hi>ſubject</hi> as well worthy of a <hi>Princes favour,</hi> and as fit for his <hi>Counſells,</hi> that he is as reall, and hearty in his <hi>freindships,</hi> and hath a ſoule as full of <hi>juſtice,</hi> and <hi>honour</hi> as is any where to be found.</p>
            <p>Upon his coming to <hi>Portumna,</hi> my <hi>Lord Leiutenant</hi> meets with <hi>S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. George Monro,</hi> who was poſted thither out of the north to make ſome Propoſalls in order to the reduction of <hi>Vlſter</hi> to His <hi>Excellency</hi> &amp; my Lord of <hi>Clanricard,</hi> (who had the Summer before aſſiſted him towards his <hi>Vlſter</hi> expedition with a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment of foot 100 horſe, and 1000 pounds in mony out of the Province of <hi>Conaght;)</hi> &amp; in caſe thoſe overtures of his were not approved of, to demand his paſſe, that he might leave the <hi>Kingdome;</hi> But what he propounded, was ſo plauſible, that
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:118090:22"/> in caſe mony, and armes could be had in time, and in propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to what he demanded, (as the infection of <hi>Galloway</hi> out of which towne cheifly both were to be had, made it very difficult) they judged it a very likely expedition; Wherupon my Lord of <hi>Clanricard,</hi> deſirous to keep ſo able a commander as <hi>S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. George</hi> in the Kingdom, furnisheth him with what mony he could at the preſent, and ſends him Northward to lay, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare the buſineſſe before; promiſing to do his uttermoſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to procure him thoſe ſupplies of mony, ammunition, and armes by the time appointed; as alſo to bring his army up as farr as <hi>Sligo,</hi> there to countenance <hi>S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. George</hi> in his under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takings, and be ready for any fair occaſion, that should preſent it ſelfe for the maſtering of the Country.</p>
            <p>After four, or five daies ſtay at the moſt, His <hi>Excellency</hi> tooke his leave, and haſtened towards <hi>Kilkenny,</hi> obligeing my Lord of <hi>Clanricard</hi> to come after him, to be preſent at a meeting he had appointed there, for the procuring of a good underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing between the <hi>Clergy, the</hi> Commiſſioners, and himſelfe, and for taking the beſt order they could for the raiſing, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayning an army againſt the next ſpring: But though they met, nothing at that time could be done, or agreed upon; Wherfore my Lord of <hi>Clanricard</hi> returnes into <hi>Connaght</hi> to take order for his <hi>Northren</hi> expedition; which out of the great dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties of getting his men together, ariſing out of the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall diſtractions, that were then in the Kingdom, the hard ſeaſon of the yeare, the Peſtilence, the want of monies, and proviſions; he could not poſſibly go through with, againſt <hi>February</hi> which was the time deſigned; Nor even then, when he did, without very great neceſſities, and inconveniences to himſelfe, and his army, as I can well witneſſe, having
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:118090:23"/> had the honour to waite upon him moſt part of that journey.</p>
            <p>This failing in Point of time, and a great part of the monies promiſed him, (which nevertheleſſe as things ſtood no mans Induſtry could have remedied) <hi>S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. George Monro</hi> complained very much of, affirming that their opportunity was loſt ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by; eſpecially now they being come, the army was able to move no further, through extream want of Proviſions (kept from them by foule &amp; contrary weather) for which, &amp; the reſidue of the mony, together with hopes of an accord between my <hi>Lord Leiutenant;</hi> and the <hi>Commiſsioners</hi> ſome daies were ſpent in Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation, but nothing coming in the end, except only a letter from my Lord of <hi>Ormond</hi> ſummoning my Lord of <hi>Clanricard,</hi> ſuddainly away; his <hi>Lordship</hi> was forced to leave his army, and the Northren buſineſſe to the hazard, and return back to meet my <hi>Lord Leiutenant,</hi> and the <hi>Commiſsioncrs</hi> at <hi>Loghreogh:</hi> Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon <hi>Sr. George Monro</hi> beleiving now that my <hi>Lord Leiutenant</hi> would leave the Kingdom, ſeing the diviſions amongſt the <hi>Irish</hi> grow daily greater, and giving all for loſt, and laſtly find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the impatience of his own party to treat with the enemy, (as he had often before publiquely declared he would) retires himſelfe to <hi>Eniskillin,</hi> and having made Conditions for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, the remainder of his Party, and his Officers that were in priſon, gave up that place to the enemy, &amp; departed the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. Very ſoone after whoſe retirement, my Lord of <hi>Clanricards</hi> army for extremity of want was forced to returne from <hi>Sligo</hi> back towards the <hi>County</hi> of <hi>Galway.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where I will leave it, and come back unto his <hi>Excellency,</hi> who being left by my Lord <hi>Clanricard</hi> lately in <hi>Kilkenny,</hi> after having cauſed Captain <hi>Tickle</hi> to be executed for a deſign he had of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traying that town unto <hi>Cromwell;</hi> was by the breach growing
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:118090:23"/> daily wider between him, &amp; the Kingdom, and through the encreaſe of the ſickneſs now come thither, at the joynt requeſt of the <hi>Commiſsioners,</hi> and <hi>Officers,</hi> induced to remove towards <hi>Lymerick,</hi> where being negligently received without the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed reſpect uſed to the <hi>Kings Leiutenant,</hi> he after a short ſtay departed thence into the County of <hi>Clare.</hi> Immediately therupon, the enemy having refreshd his men, and encreaſed his army, with a great acceſſion of old ſouldiers, that had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly ſerved under my <hi>Lord Inchiquin</hi> and my <hi>Lord Leiutenant,</hi> takes the feild, and falls a ſummoning Caſtles, and bringing the Country under Contribution, wherin he had a generall ſucceſs, moſt of the Caſtles ſurrendring upon appearance of a party of horſe, except <hi>Kiltenan,</hi> which gave him ſome reſiſtance.</p>
            <p>His <hi>Excellencies</hi> army through the forementioned obſtinacy, and diſobedience of the townes againſt receiving Garriſons, was ſo farr diſperſed, that there was no meanes of drawing them together; Neither, if that were done, of keeping them in a body, for the Country was deſtroyed, and waſt, ſo that it could not ſupply him; beſides during theſe diſagrements between my <hi>Lord Leiutenant,</hi> the <hi>Clergy,</hi> and the <hi>Commiſsioners</hi> there were few, or none of the <hi>Irish</hi> ſouldiers (if there had been Proviſions for them) that would obey his <hi>Excellencies</hi> Orders. Of all which <hi>Cromwell</hi> was well aware, and therfore went ſecurely, and with confidence to work, carrying all before him: A mongſt other of his ſucceſſes, <hi>Balliſonan</hi> is ſold unto him, and <hi>Cahir Caſtle</hi> (then the dwelling houſe of <hi>Maſter Mathewes</hi> a yong youth, and halfe Brother to my <hi>Lord Leiutenant)</hi> given him contrary to thoſe ſtrict orders left by his <hi>Excellency</hi> with <hi>Maſter Mathewes</hi> for the keeping of it; who was ſo conſcious of his own miſdoing in the act, that he refuſed upon ſeverall ſummons, and invitations
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:118090:24"/> to appear before my <hi>Lord,</hi> &amp; ſtaied ſtill in the enemies quarters to ſecure himſelfe from His <hi>Excellencies</hi> indignation. But ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſſe this act of <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Matthewes</hi> is made aground of new ſuſpitions, and fresh clamours againſt my <hi>Lord</hi> himſelfe by the <hi>Irish,</hi> who all this while run on in their extravagancies, intent only upon their diſputes in hand, as if there were no ſuch man as <hi>Cromwell</hi> in the Kingdom; in ſo much, that ſeing ſo many ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall meetings aſſigned, and ſo much time ſpent to ſo litle purpoſe, His <hi>Excellency</hi> concludes that thoſe people would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be brought into order by <hi>him,</hi> and therfore reſolves to withdraw himſelfe from the Government, if not to depart the Kingdom, and to commit the mannagement of all unto the Marquis of <hi>Clanricard,</hi> which was the reaſon of his Lordships being ſent for back from <hi>Sligo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The enemy in the meane time having the Caſtles of <hi>Gowran,</hi> and <hi>Laghlin,</hi> together with the Officers commanding in them delivered into his hands by the common ſouldiers, ſets at laſt upon <hi>Kilkenny;</hi> Whence a while before the Earle of <hi>Caſtle-haven,</hi> (who was now left with cheife command in <hi>Leinſter)</hi> was drawn out with his forces, by reaſon the ſickneſſe raged ſo, leaving <hi>S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Walter Butler,</hi> and <hi>Major Walsh</hi> with about 50 horſe, and ſome 400 foot in the place, where a breach being made, and the enemy aſſaulting, they were bravely repulſed, leaving 600 armes behind them; after which check, they reſolved, to march of, and are ſending their artillery away ſilently before, whilſt the townſmen conuay a drummer privately over the wall, and upon I know not what accord, let the enemy in, unknown to the ſouldiers, who were then forced to retire to the Caſtle, &amp; make their termes, which being granted them, they march away.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Kilkenny</hi> being gained by him, let us leaue <hi>Cromwell</hi> at <hi>Cashell</hi>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:118090:24"/> for a while amongſt his <hi>Committee</hi> men, &amp; returne into <hi>Connaght,</hi> where the <hi>Cleargy,</hi> and <hi>Commiſsioners</hi> ſeing that my Lord of <hi>Clanricard</hi> having refuſed to take the Government upon him was reſolved in caſe, they continued diſobedient unto my <hi>Lord Leiutenant</hi> (leaſt the <hi>Kings Authority</hi> should bee expoſed to further diſobedience &amp; contempt) to leave the Kingdom toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with His <hi>Excellency,</hi> &amp; conſidering what a certain ruine their departure would be unto them all; are now courting my <hi>Lord Leiuteuant</hi> to ſtay, and offer to come to compoſition with him: who demands aſſurance from them that the reſpective towns of <hi>Lymerick,</hi> and <hi>Gallway</hi> shall receive ſufficient Guarriſons, and that themſelves with all the ſoldiers, &amp; people shall hereafter readily obay him; Which they undertake unto him, upon condition that all the <hi>English</hi> what ſoever under his <hi>Excellencies</hi> command might be disbanded, and ſent away; that the <hi>Bishops</hi> of the Kingdom might have a share in Councell, and the mannagement of things; that the Receiver Generall (which was <hi>S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. George Hamilton</hi> Brother in law to my <hi>Lord Leiutenant</hi> a perſon of great parts, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and merit) might give in his accounts; all which his <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency,</hi> out of his great deſire to ſatisfy, and unite the people therby to preſerve the <hi>Country,</hi> and the <hi>Kings Intereſt</hi> (if it were poſſible) at laſt aſſents unto.</p>
            <p>This agreement being made, the <hi>English</hi> were accordingly (to free the <hi>Irish</hi> of their jealouſies, who either were, or would ſeem to be equally ſuſpitious of the Cavaliers, as of thoſe, that had ſerved the <hi>Parliament</hi> before) disbanded, and ſince there was no further employment for them, nor meanes of getting away by ſea, they had leave to make their conditions with <hi>Cromwell,</hi> to paſſe through his quarters out of the Kingdom, which being granted by him, all the ſmall remainder of my Lord of <hi>Inchiquins</hi>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:118090:25"/> men, (except a few that Colonell <hi>Buller</hi> was to Carry for <hi>Scil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly)</hi> went under the conduct of Colonell <hi>John Daniell</hi> into the enemies quarters; ſo did my Lord of <hi>Ardes,</hi> and after him, <hi>S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Thomas Armſtrong,</hi> with whom went alſo <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Daniell O Neille</hi> upon the Score of carying a Regiment into Spaine, There remained none behind, that was permitted to beare any charge, but Leiutenant <hi>Colonell Treſwell,</hi> at my Lord of <hi>Ormonds</hi> particular inſtance to command his Guards of <hi>horſe;</hi> only my Brother <hi>John Digby, Colonell Henry Warren,</hi> &amp; <hi>Colonell Hugh Butler</hi> ſtaid to waite upon his <hi>Excellencies</hi> Perſon, and beare him company in his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventures.</p>
            <p>But before I go on, I muſt not omit to tell you, how <hi>Dean Boile,</hi> who was ſent to treat with <hi>Cromwell</hi> for the <hi>English,</hi> that were disbanded, being offered it, as he ſaies, by <hi>Cromwell,</hi> and imagining, as himſelfe affirmes, to do a ſervice to my <hi>Lord Leiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant,</hi> &amp; my Lord <hi>Inchiquin,</hi> in it, adventured of his own head to take <hi>paſſes</hi> from him, for their departure out of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; Wherof, aſſoon as ever <hi>Dean Boile</hi> was gone, he makes uſe to debaush the <hi>Irish</hi> Garriſons, to take conditions from him, aſſuring them my Lord <hi>Leiutenant</hi> had received his paſſe to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part the Kingdom, as appeares by a letter that the Governour of <hi>Roſſe</hi> writ (it ſeemes by <hi>Cromwells</hi> order) unto Generall <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſton</hi> commanding in <hi>Waterford;</hi> the Copy of which Letter, with that of <hi>Cromwells</hi> paſſe, &amp; three of <hi>Dean Boiles</hi> Letters concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, together with his <hi>Excellencies</hi> to <hi>Cromwell,</hi> when he ſent him back his paſſe by a trumpet of my Lord <hi>Clanricards,</hi> (having procured them for my own ſatisfaction) I herewithall ſend your <hi>Lordship,</hi> that you may ſee how abſolutely without my <hi>Lord Leiutenants</hi> privity, or licenſe theſe paſſes were accepted, &amp; with what indignation reſented. <hi>Emer Mac Mahon Bishop</hi> of <hi>Cloghor,</hi>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:118090:25"/> who had been choſen Generall of the <hi>Vlſter</hi> army, having a good while ſince received his commiſſion from my <hi>Lord Leiutenant,</hi> was now gathering together his army, which in ad short time af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter (before my leaving the Kingdom) he had made up to be about 6000 men, wherewith having taken ſeverall little Caſtles in his way, he was marched up into the <hi>Claneboyes,</hi> and become maſter of the feild.</p>
            <p>The next enterprize <hi>Cromwell</hi> went in hand with, was, to take <hi>Clonmell</hi> which was kept by Major Generall <hi>Hugh O Neale,</hi> who behaved himſelfe ſo diſcreetly, &amp; gallantly in defending it, that <hi>Cromwell</hi> loſt neer upon 2500 men before it, &amp; had notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding gone away without it, if they within had had ſtore of powder; but their ſmall proportion being ſpent, the Governour with his ſouldiers was fain to go out of the town on the other ſide of the river by night towards <hi>Waterford,</hi> &amp; leave the townes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men to make conditions for themſelves; which they did the next morning, the enemy not knowing but the Garriſon was ſtill in towne, till the conditions were ſigned. Thus the loſſe of this place, &amp; ſeverall other Garriſons, for want of ammunition, was another effect of the diſobedience of the townes; In ſo much, that had it not been for a little magazine, that my Lord of <hi>Clanricard</hi> had providently made before hand, &amp; wherewith, ſince the loſſe of <hi>Drogheda,</hi> his <hi>Excellencies</hi> army, the <hi>Scots,</hi> the <hi>Vlſters,</hi> &amp; moſt of the Garriſons were ſurnished; All might have gone to an irrecoverable ruine, whilſt the walld townes like free States lookt on, as unconcernd, denying to afford it to them.</p>
            <p>This being true, no body that hath heard of any injuries, or injuſtice in point of trade, or prizes here, can blame the <hi>King,</hi> or my <hi>Lord Leiutenant</hi> for it, neither of whom they did obey, further then they pleaſd themſelves, but now having received Garriſons, (as I make no queſtion they have) I dare be bold to aſſure any body, that trafficks that way, of all equity, &amp; juſtice
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:118090:26"/> from my <hi>Lord Leiutenant</hi> hands. About the time of the ſeidge of <hi>Clonmell, David Roch</hi> having raiſed above 2000 men in the Counties of <hi>Corke,</hi> &amp; <hi>Kerry,</hi> and beginning to make head with them, received a ſmall brush from my Lord of <hi>Broghall,</hi> which only diſperſed his men for a few daies, his loſſe being not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable for any thing, but the <hi>Bishop</hi> of <hi>Roſſe,</hi> who being taken was hanged with two other <hi>Prieſts</hi> by <hi>Cromwell,</hi> for being found in armes (as they ſaid) againſt the <hi>Right worshipfull</hi> the <hi>State</hi> of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Soone after the gaining of <hi>Clonwell, Cromwell,</hi> upon letters out of <hi>England,</hi> inviting him thither, goes to ſea, and leaves <hi>Ireton</hi> in cheife command behind him, to ſubdue the reſt of that miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable waſted Kingdom, whilſt himſelfe went about the conqueſt of new <hi>Empires,</hi> more worthy of his preſence; But ſince he is gone, I cannot but here obſerve, that of all thoſe <hi>thouſands,</hi> that either came with him thither, or were ſent after, there are now few <hi>hundreds</hi> ſurviving, either to reap the benefit, or report the ſtories of their Victories; his army upon his departure being ſunke to a very inconſiderable number, eſpecially in foot, and neer three parts of thoſe conſiſting of either <hi>Irish, Jones,</hi> or my Lord of <hi>Inchiquins</hi> men, who only are able to undergo the wofull incommodities of that Country, now groning under a univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall <hi>plague famine,</hi> and <hi>deſolation,</hi> to that degree, that if they knew but halfe the miſery that expects them there, I am confident that no threats, nor flatteries, could perſwade men out of <hi>England</hi> thither, in hopes of reaping the fruites of their fellowes labours in that deſtroyed Kingdom. Which, as low as tis brought, may chance to coſt <hi>Cromwell</hi> a ſecond expedition, and another army, and yet go without it.</p>
            <p>For they have <hi>Waterford, Galloway,</hi> and <hi>Limrick</hi> three of the ſtrongeſt, and moſt conſiderable townes of the Kingdom ſtill untaken, any of which, if they be well Garriſond (as queſtionleſs
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:118090:26"/> now they are) will be neare a ſummers work to reduce; The forts of <hi>Duncannon,</hi> &amp; <hi>Silgo,</hi> the Caſtles of <hi>Caterlo, Athlone, Charlemont</hi> &amp; <hi>Neauagh</hi> are not eaſy puachaſes; the <hi>Province</hi> of <hi>Connaght</hi> is ſtill preſerved intire by my Lord of <hi>Clanricard,</hi> who will be able to bring 4000 men of his own into the feild, now that <hi>Galloway</hi> &amp; his Country is ſomewhat cleard from the infection of the plague; which begins to rage greatly in the enemies quarters, as <hi>Cork Youghall, Wexford,</hi> and <hi>Dublin</hi> it ſelfe; <hi>Kilkenuy, Clonmell,</hi> with ſeverall places there abouts being left deſolate with it. The County of <hi>Clare</hi> in <hi>Mounſter</hi> brought unto my <hi>Lord Leiutenant</hi> at a <hi>Rendezvous</hi> juſt upon my coming away, above 2000 men wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with his <hi>Excellency</hi> being invited by the Magiſtrates was ready to march into <hi>Limrick</hi> for to Garriſon the place, and to make it his reſidence</p>
            <p>What Forces the <hi>Irish</hi> had in <hi>Vlſter,</hi> &amp; towards <hi>Kerry,</hi> I have already told you, as likewiſe what <hi>Connaght,</hi> and the County of <hi>Clare</hi> afforded: I muſt add that <hi>Hugh Mac Phelim</hi> had in <hi>Wicklow,</hi> &amp; towards <hi>Wexford,</hi> hard upon 2000 men, &amp; at <hi>Waterford.</hi> Generall <hi>Preſton</hi> and <hi>Hugh O Neale</hi> had litle leſſe; to conclude beſides all this the <hi>Lord Caſtlehaven,</hi> the <hi>Lord Dillon,</hi> and the <hi>Bishop</hi> of <hi>Drum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more,</hi> made account they should draw together a conſiderable body in <hi>Meath,</hi> and the reſt of <hi>Leinſter</hi> to joyne with the Marquis of <hi>Clanricard</hi> towards, the releife of <hi>Tecroghan,</hi> then beſeidged by Colonell <hi>Reynolds.</hi> Thus your Lordship may ſee that (provided they bee united amongſt themſelves) (as truly I left them) and that meanes can be found of keeping them in bodies together, there are men enough in armes yet to diſpute the buſineſs with an enemy, that is not halfe their number, &amp; whoſe quarters are peſtered likewiſe with the plague, and famine, as well as theirs, eſpecially theſe having ſuch ſtrengths, and faſtneſſes, ſtill in their hands, as are almoſt inacceſſible to <hi>Cromwells</hi> ſouldiers. Who after having maſtered the greateſt part of <hi>Mounſter,</hi> and
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:118090:27"/> 
               <hi>Leinſter,</hi> and their ſupplies from <hi>England</hi> coming in but ſlowly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> have made bold at laſt with the people they flattered with be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, &amp; altered their manner of proceedings, taking from them by force what they pleaſed, and violating their protections gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; making not nice to tell them, they ſuffered them to poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe their eſtates but during pleaſure, and till they could have <hi>planters</hi> to put into their roomes; by which kind of clear dealing they have ſo loſt, &amp; made deſperate the natives, that lamenting their former too ready compliance with the enemy, they now call for my <hi>Lord Leiutenant</hi> again, &amp; taking armes in their hande begin to riſe in all quarters of the Kingdom, ſo that it is impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for a greater power then <hi>Ireton</hi> has there to attend to the ſuppreſſion of them all.</p>
            <p>In this poſture left I that Kingdom, it being very probable, that if the enemies recruites, and proviſions out of <hi>England</hi> did faile through any other diverſion, and the <hi>Irish</hi> receive but any moderate ſupplies from abroad, they would not only make good all that was left them, But alſo recouer upon the enemy conſiderably this Summer, which really I wish with all my ſoule they may, Principally for His MAjESTIES ſake, and the preſent engagement of the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland,</hi> to both which the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of what is left, or the regaining of what is loſt in <hi>Irland,</hi> muſt needs be, if well conſidered, of high concernment; And in the next place for the ſake of many worthy families amongſt them, ſome of which were never involved in the aſſociation, nor had any hand in the warr, and many of the reſt, through the menaces &amp; ſtrange kind of proceedings of the <hi>Parliament</hi> againſt the whole Nation upon the Inſurrection, &amp; the villanous prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſes of <hi>Parſons,</hi> &amp; <hi>Burlacy,</hi> the then Lords <hi>Juſtices</hi> who deſired to make them all forfeit their eſtates, were frighted &amp; forced into Rebellion. All which are now to ſuffer equally, and by <hi>Cromwell</hi> with out diſtinction deſigned for ruine, together with thoſe, that
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:118090:27"/> were the <hi>Originall</hi> authors of the firſt Rebellion, and thoſe ugly maſſacres, that were committed: which indeed deſerves commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeration, ſince very many of the Nobility, &amp; gentry, with the body of the people wish the <hi>King</hi> as well, &amp; have as great diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions to his ſervice, as can be deſired, having been abuſed who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> into thoſe offences they have committed, by a few malicious ill affected perſons, craftier then moſt of the reſt; Who ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> with great art, and induſtry acquired unto themſelves the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of wiſe, religious, and honeſt men: Wherby they miſlea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that credulous, and for the moſt part unwiſe Nation, upon pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of the advancement of their <hi>Roman Religion,</hi> and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of their Country, to what they pleaſe.</p>
            <p>Having been able to perſwade them, that all theſe afflictions, &amp; misfortunes they ſuffer under, are come upon them for their admitting of a <hi>ceſſation,</hi> &amp; a <hi>peace</hi> indiſobedience to the <hi>Nuntio,</hi> &amp; for their joyning with <hi>Heretiques;</hi> Not ſuffering them to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider rightly, that it is their diſobedience to the lawfull <hi>King,</hi> &amp; the blood, and murther they are guilty of that, makes them ſo unfortunate, that is their breaches of publike faith in compliance with the <hi>Nuntio,</hi> the rapine, and want of juſtice, that raignes amongſt them, that hath brought upon them theſe heavy pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishments, &amp; given them over to be ſcourged by the hand of ſo <hi>faithleſs,</hi> &amp; <hi>Bloody an enemy.</hi> And ſurely whoſoever shall recollect how firſt, after the double breach of the former peace, they were immediately punished with the defeat of two conſiderable armies, one after another; with the deſolation of the flourishing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt part of their Country; upon which a famine enſued, that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured neer 20000 ſoules, then how the plague, that hath ſince over ſpread the Kingdom, began firſt at <hi>Galloway</hi> the place that did moſt, &amp; longeſt countenance thoſe ill proceedings of the <hi>Nuntio,</hi> &amp; <hi>O Neale,</hi> of any other in the Kingdom; where it ſwept away about 5000 ſoules, &amp; thoſe only of the common, and
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:118090:28"/> meaneſt ſort of people, who were they, that contrary to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations of the principall perſons (being moſt of them mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, &amp; well diſpoſed men) carried all things their violent way.</p>
            <p>Next how the <hi>Vlſter</hi> army, which I heare have received a great defeat ſince my coming away) who were the beginners of the rebellion, the breakers of the firſt Peace, the oppoſers of the ſecond, &amp; the releivers of <hi>Derry,</hi> are now come to fall under the hands of <hi>Coote,</hi> &amp; thoſe men, who, if it had not been for them, had certainly been deſtroyed; And laſtly how the <hi>Bishops</hi> of <hi>Tuam,</hi> &amp; <hi>Cloghor,</hi> who had ſo deep hands in the contrivance of the warr, &amp; were guilty of ſo much blood, have both fallen (if the printed relation concerning the laſt of them be true) upon the edge of the ſworde, together with their armies The <hi>Bishops</hi> of <hi>Roſſe,</hi> &amp; <hi>Downe</hi> alſo, (the firſt of which had, not many weekes before his own miſcarriage, appeared very unhandſomely in the perſecution of the <hi>Proteſtant Lord Bishop</hi> of <hi>London Derry,</hi> a perſon of great worth, moderation, and prudence, &amp; one; Who, as he had meritted highly from the <hi>King</hi> for his loyalty, and conſtant ſervices, ſo, alſo was he very farr to my knowledge, from deſerving ill from that Kingdom; The ſecond, one, who had ever cherished ſtirrs &amp; factions, &amp; both of them notoriouſly averſe to peace, &amp; to the Government, coming to perish igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniouſly in the hands of thoſe enemies, (that by ſtaving off a timely ſubmiſſion to the <hi>Kings</hi> Authority, &amp; hindering the ſettle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Country) they may be ſaid, after a ſort, to have brought into the Kingdom. He muſt needs, as I do, admire the order of <hi>Gods Chaſtiſements,</hi> with ſubmiſſion acknowledging that he is juſt, and that his judgements are right.</p>
            <p>Through whoſe fault, or through what miſcarriage, <hi>Tecroghan</hi> is loſt after it hath been ſo long and gallantly defended by <hi>S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Robert Talbot,</hi> and the lady <hi>Fitz-Garret,</hi> and the <hi>Vlſter</hi> army de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feated, I cannot undertake to ſay, ſince they are accidents after
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:118090:28"/> my coming to ſea, Though I do much feare that the firſt was occaſioned principally through the reliques of thoſe unhappy <hi>emulations</hi> &amp; <hi>backwardneſſes</hi> that dwelt in ſome of the great ones againſt others who were like to reap too much honour and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage from the enterprize in caſe that place had been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leived and preſerved.</p>
            <p>What ever the matter were I confeſs thoſe miſchances have much altered the caſe from what it was, but yet I deſpaire not of the buſineſs in giving all for gone, but hope <hi>Gods juſtice</hi> having been in ſome meaſure ſatisfied, &amp; the people being be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come more humble, &amp; more united, that by <hi>Gods</hi> bleſſing they may weather this ſtorm, &amp; preſerve themſelves with that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to the <hi>King.</hi> However I am confident this late defeat of the <hi>Vlſter</hi> army under the conduct of the <hi>Bishop</hi> of <hi>Cloghor</hi> by ſo ſmall a party will convince the people, that theſe misfortunes are not entailed unto either my <hi>Lord</hi> of <hi>Ormonds</hi> perſon, or reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, &amp; conduce much to ſatisfy them, that his <hi>Excellency</hi> hath neither betraied the <hi>Kings</hi> Intereſt, nor them into this low con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition they are brought into; Of which being once perſwaded, they will turn their hearts, &amp; fixe their hopes wholy upon the <hi>Kings Leiutenant;</hi> Who, beleeve me my <hi>Lord,</hi> is as <hi>Wiſe,</hi> as <hi>Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable,</hi> &amp; <hi>Gallant a Perſon</hi> as is any where to be found, &amp; as <hi>excellent a ſubject,</hi> as any <hi>Prince</hi> in the world can boaſt of; Yea and one who, I aſſure your Lordship, (if ever he shall thinke it fit to give the world an account of his actions) is able with <hi>modeſty,</hi> &amp; <hi>truth</hi> to ſay ſo much for himſelfe, and for what he hath done, as will wring a confeſſion out of the mouth of <hi>enuy</hi> herſelfe, that hee hath behaved himſelfe ſo <hi>prudently,</hi> &amp; ſo <hi>uprightly</hi> in the place he now holds notwithſtanding all theſe forementioned <hi>misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes,</hi> that no man hath ever out gone him in <hi>loyalty</hi> to, or <hi>merit</hi> from the <hi>Crowne</hi> and <hi>Royall houſe</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> of which a better ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument needs not be given then that moſt <hi>Excellent Speech</hi> (for
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:118090:29"/> the eloquence, and ſubject of it deſerving an <hi>Eternall Memory)</hi> delivered by his own mouth unto the <hi>Generall Aſſembly</hi> of the <hi>Confederates</hi> upon the concluſion of the <hi>Peace</hi> wherin you will find the <hi>Principles</hi> he goes upon, ſo <hi>Loyall,</hi> and ſo <hi>Vnbyaſſed;</hi> The <hi>Treaſons, Defections,</hi> and <hi>Impaciencies</hi> of the people that have faln out ſince, through the nationall <hi>animoſities</hi> particular <hi>factions</hi> and <hi>preſſures</hi> of the warr ſo prudently <hi>foreſeen,</hi> &amp; ſo <hi>Prophetically foretold,</hi> that thoſe perſons (of what Nation ſoever they bee) muſt be as <hi>blind</hi> as they are <hi>Malicious</hi> that shall attribute any of thoſe mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortuns that have enſued, either to want of <hi>Abilities</hi> or <hi>Fidelity</hi> in my <hi>Lord Leiutenant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherfore I <hi>Lordship</hi> (if any where it ſeeme leſſe clear, and ſatisfactory, then you could wish) not to looke upon this short account I have given, as upon all that might have been ſaid upon the ſubject, for theſe being only reflections of my own, and delivered in ſuch haſt, it is no wonder, if ſome things be mistaken, and more forgot, by him that is with all the duty and affection in the world:</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Nobleſt Lord</salute>
               <signed>Your <hi>Lordships</hi> moſt devoted humble ſervant LEWIS DYVE.</signed>
               <dateline>From the <hi>Hague</hi> 
                  <date>Iuly the 10. 1650. 20.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letters">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:118090:29"/>
            <head>THE COPIES. Of the ſeverall LETTERS Mentioned by S<hi rend="sup">R</hi>. LEVVIS DYVE In the foregoing Diſcourſe.</head>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>A Letter of the <hi>Marquis</hi> of <hi>Clanricard</hi> to <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Walſingham</hi> Secretary to my Brother the <hi>Lord Digby</hi> concerning his <hi>Lordships taking armes In defence of the Ceſſation-mentioned.</hi> PAG. 6.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>WORTHY COVSEN,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>THough at a late houre, accept of my thankfull acknowledgements for the frequent intelligences and adviſes I have received from you; though the obſtructions they mett within their Paſſage to mee, and their finding mee engaged in the remoteſt parts of the Kingdome, did not afford me opportunity to keep the like Correſpondence with you, nor reap the full benefit of your advertiſements: which a more quick and ſeaſonable convayance might have produced. But now, not knowing what, or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther any right information hath gone from hence of our paſt proceedings, I hold it not impertinent (having met with ſo ſure a meſſenger) to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine you with ſome breife notions of them, Conceiving your friendſhip and reſpect to mee, will take of the Scandall of any vanity or oſtenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:118090:30"/> in mee to bee the true relator of my own ſtory unto you in theſe diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous times.</p>
               <p>Vpon my <hi>Lord Lieutenants</hi> and my <hi>Lord Digbyes</hi> departure (having deve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted my ſelfe of that ſmall power then remaining with mee, and ſequeſtred my thoughts from ingageing in any buſineſſe) I retired to ſome Caſtles of mine near the ſea ſide, with an intention together with my family to ſhip for <hi>France;</hi> but not ſo ſetled in that reſolution as not to bee inclined to weather out the ſtorme, as long as I could diſcerne any probability of ſafety in that ſolytary retirement, in which I remained untill my Lord of <hi>Inchiquin</hi> declared for the <hi>King,</hi> and that intelligence was brought mee of my <hi>Lord Lieutenants</hi> arrivall in <hi>France;</hi> and the probability of his returne hither in his former Command.</p>
               <p>Then upon Conſideration of the Condition of affaires in order to the <hi>Kings</hi> ſervice, (though the diſtemper of this miſerable age could not afford me ſuch authorities as might ſecure my undertaking) I thought it a ſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and becoming duty in mee to appear abroad, and make ſome tryall how the people ſtood affected towards a ſetlement: Whereupon finding many friends well diſpoſed, and willing to run any hazard with mee rather then admitt of my departure out of the <hi>Kingdome:</hi> I put on a reſolution to appear in armes in oppoſition to <hi>Generall O Neales,</hi> and the <hi>Nuntios faction,</hi> who were then grown very ſtrong and reſolved both to breake the preſent government, and overthrow all overtures towards a peace.</p>
               <p>In breife after I had framed and publiſhed a declaration (which I am confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent you have ſeen ere this, and therein obſerved the ſtreights I was put unto to keep my ſelfe within due limits, and to make it likewiſe ſatisfactory to thoſe parties whoſe aſsiſtance was neceſſary for mee.) I procured my Lord <hi>Taaffe</hi> and a party of my Lord of <hi>Inchiquins</hi> to come and joyn themſelves unto thoſe forces I had raiſed; whereupon wee advanced towards <hi>Owen O Neale</hi> then at <hi>Athlone,</hi> who though he exceeded us in number marcht away through the counties of <hi>Roſcommon</hi> and <hi>Letrim</hi> cleerly out of <hi>Conaght:</hi> Whereby I recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the ſtrong caſtle of <hi>Athlone</hi> (formerly as you know ſo deſtructively and ſo unſeaſonably loſt) <hi>Iames Town</hi> a very conſiderable place, the <hi>Mote, Elphin,</hi> &amp; ſeverall other holds of ſtrength and conſequence; by which meanes, and by the committall of ſome principall factions perſons, having ſetled the lower parts of the province. I returned homewards; where ſome rebellious perſons and others of the county of <hi>Mayo</hi> aſſociated with the town of <hi>Galway,</hi> and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the advantage of my abſence had ſurprized ſome Caſtles of mine, and ſtopt the armes and ammunition I had contracted for at <hi>Galway.</hi> But after ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving blockt up that town I brought them to a ſubmiſsion within three weekes, and to pay a conſiderable ſum of mony: Beſides all which J would have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced them to take in a <hi>Gurriſon</hi> but that I was neceſsitated to haſten away, and attend <hi>Owen O Neales</hi> motions; who having fetcht a great compaſſe was gotten
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:118090:30"/> into <hi>Ormond,</hi> and had ſurprized the <hi>Neanagh</hi> (a ſtrong Caſtle of my <hi>Lord Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenants</hi> tenanted by young <hi>Sr. George Hamilton)</hi> after which he tooke the <hi>Birr</hi> in the <hi>Kings County,</hi> and then <hi>Fort falkland;</hi> a fort of the <hi>Kings</hi> which had a dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Proſpect towards mee; giving him paſſage over the River within ſeaven miles of <hi>Portumna.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But by the time I was drawn of from <hi>Galway</hi> and gotten home, I received in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence from my <hi>Lord</hi> of <hi>Inchiquin</hi> that he was in purſuite of <hi>Oneile</hi> and had by ſtorm regained the <hi>Neanagh,</hi> and likewiſe <hi>Birr;</hi> And finding him deſirous of the aſsiſtance of my forces to attempt <hi>Fort falkland,</hi> I repaired immediately unto him, with a conſiderable party of horſe and foot: When being ready at laſt to fall upon the fort, my Lords Officers tired with foule weather, and long Marches after <hi>Oneile</hi> would not be perſuaded to ſtay: But whilſt this was in diſpute (moſt luckily as it fell out) <hi>Owen O Neale</hi> with 7000. foot, and 500. horſe clapt down hard by us in aſtreight of <hi>Bogge</hi> and <hi>woode</hi> and therby utterly obſtructed our paſſage back; ſo that our army being forced to ſtay I prevaild that my men with my <hi>Lords Battery</hi> ſhould attend upon the fort, whilſt my Lords army did face <hi>Owen O Neale:</hi> Whereby after a day or two battering, the <hi>fort</hi> was ſurrendred to us; &amp; <hi>O Neale</hi> who thought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o ſtarve us had that lot him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, being, forced to ſteal away in the night; and then I having plentifully ſupplyed the army by boate out of the county of <hi>Galway)</hi> his Lordſhip had a free paſſage back, leaving me in the poſſeſsion of the <hi>fort</hi> much to my advantage and ſecurity. Soon after which to perfect our Good Succeſſe, we received certain notice of my <hi>Lord Lieutenants</hi> being landed at <hi>Cork,</hi> which concludes this ſtory.</p>
               <p>I ſhall not need to enlarge my ſelfe upon the happy concluding of the <hi>peace,</hi> and the great difficulties we overcame; they will come fully repreſented unto you by ſeverall wayes. J ſhall only expreſſe my confidence that wee are now ſecured from any ſecond revolutions amongſt theſe people, though the <hi>Marquis of Antrim</hi> &amp; <hi>Owen O Neale</hi> have not yet ſubmitted, for I conceive they are not ſo conſiderable but they will be ſoon ſuppreſt if they continue obſtinate. I judge it likewiſe very poſsible that this ſummer <hi>Dublin</hi> may (if God ſo pleaſe) be recovered either by force or treaty. And now beleeving I have tired you with this tedious imperfect relation, I ſhall with brevity and much truth give you aſſurance that you ſhall conſtantly find mee.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your very affectionate Couſen CLANRICARDE.</signed>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Kilkenny Caſtle</hi> 
                     <date>the 26. of <hi>Ianuary</hi> 1648.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:118090:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>A Letter of <hi>Mr. Walſinghams</hi> to Colonell <hi>Jones</hi> Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of <hi>Dublin</hi> in juſtification of <hi>the peace of Yrland, and in reply to his ſecond</hi> anſwer to my <hi>Lord Lieutenant.</hi> Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, PAG. 8.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SR.</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>HAvinge been at laſt ſo much beholdinge to your vanity, as ſome daîes ſince to meete with thoſe papers in printe that I long before heard were tranſmitted betweene my <hi>Lord Lieutenant</hi> and your ſelfe; which I perceive his <hi>Excellencies</hi> modeſty &amp; ſcorne would have ſtill concealed, had not your itch to have your confidence, and clearkeſhip known, tranſported you ſo far beyond diſcretion as to ſnatch at the occaſion of publiſhing my <hi>Lord Lieutenants</hi> letters (though ſuch indeed as if your care and prudence in manageing the cauſe you plead for, were not far inferior to your owne vaineglory you would induſtriouſly have ſmothered) to the end you might not want ſome pretence to intrude upon the world together with them, thoſe manifeſt Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vills, and leane diſcourſes of yours that are ſtuft with nothing ſingular but inſolence, and malice. And finding that his <hi>Excellency</hi> with a generous neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect both of your perſon and impertinence (with whom his publicke zeale, and duty to the <hi>King</hi> and Kingdome had enduced him to take thy paines, and deſcend ſo low) had now as one unworthy of ſo much honor, and incapable of ſo much reaſon as was preſt upon you, given you over.</p>
               <p>Notwithſtanding as well for juſtice ſake that you might not want the right of an encounter from a more equall hand then my <hi>Lord Lieutenant,</hi> as alſo for that poſsibly there may be (as I beleive there are) ſome men ſo weake and ſo willing to be deceived, that your impudence and fallacies ſhall paſſe for rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons with them if not replied unto; I thought it fit that your laſt voluminous and peremptory Letter be not let paſſe unſcand, and brought unto the teſt by a more familiar pen; that may with decency deale roundly with you, &amp; give you (what you cannot receive from his <hi>Excellencie)</hi> the confuſion of an <hi>foyle.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Though for man to thinke either with reaſon or language to contribute to the ſatisfaction of any diſcreet unprejudiced perſon, much leſſe to the recti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieing your miſtakes after my Lord of <hi>Ormond</hi> hath gone before: is a ſottiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe as great as yours, who after two addreſſes from his <hi>Excellencie</hi> ſo civill, ſo full of prudence, &amp; unanſwerable truth, had the face to tell him you were no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:118090:31"/> ſatisfied therewithall, nor any way convinced in judgement thereby.</p>
               <p>By which affirmation of how much impudence and malice you are convic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by your ſelfe, I leave you and the world to gather out of what I ſhall here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after ſay; which I am confident will convince other men aſwell as you (that know it well enough already) that your judgment was drownd in ambitious, and ſelfe intereſts ſo abſurd, and ſo ill byaſſed, that ſince reaſon and juſtice were inconſiſtent with them, you had no will to be rectified.</p>
               <p>For if you had, ſurely you would never have produced arguments to cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor your perſiſting withall; that well examined perſwad point blanck againſt, and may be returned with a double force upon you; (unleſſe you did it out of ſo invincible a ſimplicity (as to deale painely with you) is not compatible with that hipocriſy &amp; ſophiſtry your <hi>unmannerly</hi> epiſtle ſwels withall; as I now come ro inſtance particaliarly unto you.</p>
               <p>In the firſt place you hold forth the <hi>proteſtant religion</hi> for a <hi>baby</hi> to the people, and alas good man your compaſsion and care of it is very great, aſwell beco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes the ſonne unto a <hi>Biſhop,</hi> and one imbued both by education and many yeares profeſsion with it, you ſay you ſee not how it can be advanced by an army of <hi>Papiſts,</hi> nor how it can be ſecured in the peace no proviſion being made for it therin: yet that tis no ſuch miracle (they being ſecured of their owne libertie of conſcience) that an army of <hi>Catholiques,</hi> ſubjects to <hi>a prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant King,</hi> and lead by a <hi>proteſtant Generall,</hi> may in order to the reſtoreing their opreſſed ſoveraigne, and to the ſupreſsion of ſuch a <hi>Turco Iudaiſme</hi> as is now on foot be induced unto it; and that it is no new thing in the world for men to be ingaged ſo, nay (where they have no tyes of duty, nor other ſuch powerfull motives as theſe men have) directly againſt the intereſt of their owne religion, you neede but looke into the, <hi>Othoman</hi> armies where you ſhall find thouſands of <hi>Chriſtians</hi> fighting daily againſt <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> it ſelfe, and under the enſignes of <hi>France</hi> &amp; <hi>Spaine</hi> many regiments of <hi>proteſtants</hi> fighting in quarrells if you will beleive the <hi>princes</hi> themſelves purpoſely ſet on foot for the advancement of the <hi>Roman Catholique</hi> faith: which if waighed makes it nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther impoſsible nor ſtrange that the <hi>Iriſh</hi> ſhould be content to concur with any body, and almoſt upon any termes to the deſtruction of that <hi>Wild Bore</hi> who having already rooted up and overturned all government and religion in <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> is now preparing to do the like in <hi>Irland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now as for the proviſion the you find unmade for the <hi>proteſtant religion</hi> in the <hi>peace,</hi> I beleive you urge that only to ſhew your owne dexteritye in finding out objections: for you are rationall enough to know where his <hi>Majeſties authoritie</hi> is once reſtored his lawes returne to their vigor; and you ſhould be <hi>lawyer</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to know that there are lawes enough provided in this laſt foureſcore yeares for the ſecuritye of the <hi>proteſtant</hi> religion, all which the <hi>Roman Catholi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques</hi> will willingly ſubmit unto except ſuch <hi>penal ſtatutes</hi> as deprive them of the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:118090:32"/> free exerciſe of their religion, that are indeed by the <hi>peace</hi> to betaken a way, and which being laide aſide, take not any thing from the ſecurity of the <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Roman Catholiques</hi> are not the <hi>givers</hi> but the <hi>cravers</hi> here; they deſire only to ſecure their owne, not to uſurpe upon the liberty of othermens con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences; as is evident both by their daily profeſsions, and the whole trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actions of the <hi>peace,</hi> what abſurdnes then it is for any one to thinke a new pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion neceſſary; or to expect it in this caſe, that very condition for that <hi>ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my</hi> of ſixteen thouſand foot, and two thouſand five hundred horſe, with the deputation of thoſe <hi>Truſtees</hi> for to ſecure them of pardon for their paſt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, and of liberty of conſcience, with thoſe other promiſed graces and immunities againſt the ſeveritie of the lawes in force, untill all were confirmed in <hi>Parliament:</hi> to any man endued with but Comon ſenſe is a ſufficient argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; to ſay nothing of the apprehenſions (though vaine) ſtill amongſt them that they are yet not for all this ſecure enough.</p>
               <p>And what cauſe they had to inſiſt upon this <hi>army</hi> and theſe <hi>commiſsioners,</hi> do you but looke into your owne Conſcience and laying your hand upon your hart imagin ſo well of your ſelfe as that it were your owne caſe, and J am ſure you will tacitely confeſſe it is a proviſion but very reaſonable. Nay let a loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker on conſider the time theſe men tooke to ſubmit to his <hi>Majeſties authority,</hi> when he had neither meanes to puniſh, nor protect them left; and he will certainly commend their duty, and be far from diſcommending either the <hi>king</hi> or my <hi>Lord Lieutenant</hi> for any thing that in the <hi>peace</hi> is granted unto them; not excepting againſt either the number of that <hi>army,</hi> or power of thoſe <hi>Comiſsioners</hi> you make your ſelfe ſo ſcandalized withall.</p>
               <p>His <hi>Excellencie</hi> hath been already pleaſed to tell you that as to the <hi>army</hi> the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme comand thereof is in the <hi>Kings Lieutenant;</hi> the ordering of which, and diſpoſing of all future commands wherin ſo it conſiſt of, and be to <hi>Roman Catholiques</hi> will in effect be left to him; now that there are very many of that <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion</hi> inſeparable from their duty to the <hi>King,</hi> both the <hi>confederats</hi> and the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament</hi> have to their great coſt and trouble had a plentifull experience; wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe the prudent and generous <hi>Marqueſſe</hi> of <hi>Clanricard,</hi> Whoſe eminent piety and conſtancy in his <hi>profeſsion,</hi> joynd to his irreprehenſible allegiance to the <hi>King</hi> will remaine to the glory of his <hi>Nation</hi> and <hi>Religion</hi> a great and laſting <hi>exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> to future times of a firm and <hi>united Loyalty</hi> both to divine and humane <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty;</hi> as it hath ſerud the preſent already for a pattern unto ſeverall Other conſiderable perſons in <hi>Ireland</hi> to follow. And you have no reaſon but to thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke there are a good number of thoſe in this army which will ſomwhat leſſen the groundles danger you fancie to your ſelfe: eſpecially if you take alſo into conſideration the frequent wayes and diſpenſations that have bin found for entertaining very many <hi>proteſtants</hi> into ſeverall imployments in this army; and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:118090:32"/> how both theſe parties (to ſay nothing of thoſe in <hi>the north</hi> that have ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the <hi>Kings</hi> authoritie) added to that <hi>remnant army</hi> as you call them in <hi>mounſter</hi> conſiſting of about ſix thouſand men, led by an able and ſuccesful com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander (who being undeceived at laſt by the publike villanies in <hi>England</hi> have betraid themſelves (it you will have it ſo) againe into their duty will ballance any thing of ill that may be pretended in the caſe, I leave it to any one that is but capable to judge in ſuch a matter.</p>
               <p>This dangerous argument being once removed how litle remaines of hazard in that other of the power of the <hi>commiſsioners,</hi> is very evident by the articles of <hi>peace;</hi> where it is plain that their power is abſolute in nothing but the <hi>levies</hi> to be made upon their owne and that part of the peoples <hi>free holds</hi> which formerly acknowledged their <hi>Iuriſdiction,</hi> and who now had entruſted themſelves into <hi>their hands:</hi> whilſt in all the other caſes ſo induſtriouſly quoted by you (though to no other end but take up paper, and amuze the readers) they limit him as litle as formerly the <hi>counſel table</hi> did; He being able to determin nothing without their <hi>adviſe</hi> or <hi>Conſent,</hi> nor they to actuate any thing without his <hi>Commiſsion</hi> &amp; <hi>authority:</hi> which circumſcription ſhould you ſtill affirme to bee too much, would entirely vaniſh ſhould his <hi>Majeſtie</hi> com in perſon hither (as tis both hoped and beleived he will) there being no condition in the peace that li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits him.</p>
               <p>But ſuppoſe the hazard &amp; preiudice of the <hi>proteſtant religion</hi> by the peace were as great as you affirm it is, whether muſt be in fault the <hi>King,</hi> or thoſe men that preſt him to that extremity that he was only left to chooſe whether he would drown, or take hold of a <hi>brier</hi> to ſave himſelfe; whether he would utterly abandon his intereſt in all his <hi>Kingdoms</hi> to thoſe that were <hi>rebells</hi> againſt his <hi>perſon,</hi> his <hi>poſterity</hi> and <hi>Kingly</hi> power, or by giving the <hi>Iriſh</hi> whoſe <hi>rebellion</hi> could in the nature of it beare nothing ſo ill a Conſtruction thoſe not much unreaſonable conditions they ſo poſitively inſiſted upon) repoſſeſſe himſelfe of one of his three <hi>Kingdoms</hi> again, and therby becom enabled to diſpute for the other two.</p>
               <p>Thus far have I diſcourſed for the ſatisfaction of other men, with your ſelfe I might deale more breifly, and tell you it is groſſe <hi>hipocriſy</hi> for you to pretend ſo much ſollicitude for the ſecurity and advantage of the <hi>proteſtant reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion</hi> on this ſide; and yet can find them both ſufficiently provided for by an <hi>army of Sectaries</hi> on the other ſide (without any <hi>proteſtant ſuperiour</hi> to moderate them as theſe have) that have not only quite puld down the whole building of that <hi>Religion</hi> but almoſt leveld the walls of <hi>Chriſtianitie</hi> it ſelfe? by providing a <hi>libertie for all opinions</hi> and religions in the world the <hi>Catholique</hi> and <hi>proteſtant</hi> alone excepted becauſe they conceive them forſooth to be more deſtructive to the great ends of their <hi>republique</hi> then any other, the <hi>firſt,</hi> as being too <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchique,</hi> too full of <hi>Majeſty,</hi> &amp; pleading <hi>preſcription</hi> amongſt Chriſtians, with too
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:118090:33"/> much <hi>authority;</hi> and therefore likely to gain overmuch ground upon them in a time when all order &amp; religion were of the <hi>hinges,</hi> &amp; the people ſo much at a <hi>gaze;</hi> and the <hi>ſecond</hi> as being for decency &amp; order not only <hi>overpopish</hi> but alſo from its <hi>birth</hi> too much interwouen with the intereſts, of this <hi>Crown</hi> and <hi>royal familie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Can any thing be more ridiculous then, that you who derive your power from the Commanders and Commiſsioners of this <hi>army of ſaints,</hi> and who are by your <hi>Commiſsion</hi> (if I be not miſtaken) incorporated into it, having likewiſe ſet aſide the profeſsion, and exerciſe of this <hi>proteſtant religion</hi> (miſconceive me not) that Religion which for near a <hi>Century</hi> of yeares hath been practiſed &amp; eſtabliſhed in the <hi>church of England,</hi> &amp; accommodated your ſelfe clearly to <hi>Mr. Cromwells Cut</hi> (though ſuch a one as you or ſcarce himſelfe if <hi>Cathechized</hi> can give an account either of the tenents or conſtitutions of) ſhould becom ſo great a patron of, and ſo much concerned in, the intereſts of a religion that either out of <hi>Change</hi> of <hi>judgment,</hi> or out of <hi>endes</hi> (no matter which in this caſe) is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandoned by your ſelfe already.</p>
               <p>After the <hi>proteſtant religion</hi> comes the <hi>English intereſt;</hi> a conſideration indeed if urged to a perſon whoſe truſt from, and concernment in it were ſomwhat leſſe then my <hi>Lord Lieutenants,</hi> fit for you that are of <hi>English blood,</hi> and whoſe ſword &amp; pen are both by nature, and the lawes obliged to the ſervice of that <hi>crowne</hi> (in which onely, and the colonies of <hi>English</hi> here, the <hi>English intereſt</hi> of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is included) but what this <hi>English Intereſt</hi> is when we ſhall have once exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined your fright concerning it will ſoon be over; it appears to me to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but that the right and authority of the <hi>crown of England</hi> over them ſhould be acknowledged by all the <hi>ſubjects</hi> of this Kingdom; and thoſe <hi>Colonies</hi> of <hi>English,</hi> aſwell as the <hi>native Irish,</hi> be therby protected and ſecured in the poſſeſsion of ſuch fortunes, and eſtates, as either by the <hi>ſword,</hi> the <hi>roiall gift,</hi> or <hi>purchaſe</hi> have bin lawfully acquired unto them. Beyond this the <hi>English Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt</hi> is an unknown-land to me; and how far this <hi>Intereſt</hi> thus ſtated is ſecured by, or Conſiſtent with that <hi>peace</hi> you blame ſo, I leave it to any third <hi>unpreiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diced</hi> perſon to determin.</p>
               <p>Who I am certaine will find them ſquare ſo well together, that he ſhall have reaſon to beleive the <hi>Engliſh intereſt</hi> taken in your ſenſe infers an obedience to you, and your <hi>independant maſters</hi> abſtract from all relation to the <hi>crown:</hi> an eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment of your <hi>Tetrarchy</hi> here, till your ambition were wearied out, and you with your corrupt and hungry <hi>family</hi> had ungratefully glutted yourſelves in the <hi>blood and fortunes</hi> of thoſe <hi>noble perſons</hi> whoſe ſmiles and patronage in your mercenarie <hi>pleading daies</hi> were the top of your <hi>ambition;</hi> that ſo by this conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, the lives and eſtates of all that have been here in armes, may beleft a <hi>prey</hi> to worſe <hi>rebells</hi> then the worſt of theſe have ever been.</p>
               <p>This is an <hi>English intereſt</hi> indeed that the <hi>peace</hi> ſecurs not, and which I cannot blame you for pleading for with ſo much paſsion as to affirme, that <hi>were there
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:118090:33"/> neither king nor parliament you would maintaine it;</hi> neither for averring that my <hi>Lord Lieutenants</hi> tranſporting a conſiderable part of the <hi>English army</hi> hence, was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive unto: but as to the true <hi>English Intereſt</hi> I mentioned before, it was very ſuteable to that, that my <hi>Lord Lieutenant</hi> ſhould without diſpute <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>omply with the <hi>Kings</hi> commands: from whom only he had his <hi>commiſsion</hi> and derived his <hi>authoritie,</hi> and whom both himſelfe and that <hi>army</hi> in all relations both of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor and duty were obliged to obey. Beſides his <hi>Excellency</hi> knows well enough how much he was concerned in the ſupport of that <hi>cron<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ne</hi> that gave him and all the <hi>English</hi> in this Kingdome the title to what they poſſeſſed here; nothing of which could be long ſecure unto them, and the <hi>crowne</hi> at home in danger.</p>
               <p>In the next place I do not know whether the <hi>Parlement</hi> is more beholding to you for aſſerting their <hi>infringed authoriti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>;</hi> or the <hi>Irish</hi> themſelves in your being ſo generous as to let them ſee the invalidity of this <hi>peace</hi> they are abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed withall: for to prove both which you bring noworſe an argument then an <hi>English act</hi> of <hi>Parliament;</hi> which underfavour your own <hi>skil in the</hi> lawe (if you have not forgot it) will tell you can be of no force here, untill received by a <hi>Parliament</hi> in <hi>Irland:</hi> which aſſerts a power as juſt and abſolute to it ſelfe, as the <hi>Parliament</hi> of <hi>England</hi> can; elſe ſhould the <hi>ancient conquerors</hi> of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and their <hi>free poſterity,</hi> unjuſtly undergoe the <hi>dominion</hi> of thoſe, to whom neither <hi>Intereſt,</hi> nor <hi>merit</hi> hath given any <hi>right</hi> or <hi>footing</hi> here, or <hi>priviledge</hi> over them.</p>
               <p>Beſides you ſhall have others which will tell you, and make it good, that a <hi>Prince</hi> cannot give a way the <hi>Iuriſdiction of his people</hi> to one that hath no title to it (as the <hi>Parlement of England</hi> hath none to <hi>Irland)</hi> without their own conſent: yet grant for argument ſake that <hi>theſe people</hi> by taking armes unlawfully had put themſelves into that condition that might aſwell <hi>enable</hi> as <hi>induce</hi> the late <hi>King</hi> of ever glorious memory to inveſt the <hi>Parliament of England</hi> with ſuch a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer over them as <hi>that act</hi> involues; yet can it not be beleived that the <hi>King</hi> ever intended to truſt them with managing the war of <hi>Irland</hi> againſt himſelfe: as by what they have don in <hi>England</hi> tis evident they would have done; but let us alſo ſuppoſe it poſsible that the <hi>royall power</hi> can be ſo convayed unto another, as that contrary to the intention of the <hi>King</hi> it may be converted to his own deſtruction (which is a poſsition I am ſure that no <hi>Sophiſter</hi> leſſe accute, and le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arned then your ſelfe will be able to make good) yet muſt this <hi>power</hi> ſurely needs revert to its firfl originall the <hi>crown:</hi> through the death both of the <hi>King</hi> that gave it, of the <hi>Parliament</hi> it was conferd upon, and that (ſince that the <hi>Kings</hi> death is out of diſpute) this <hi>Parlement</hi> hath for this ſeaven yeares at leaſt wanted both a <hi>King</hi> and <hi>freedome</hi> which being the <hi>head</hi> and <hi>hart</hi> of that body are two things moſt neceſſary to the <hi>life</hi> and <hi>eſſence</hi> of it, nay that, that breathleſſe headles <hi>carcaſſ</hi> of a <hi>Parliament,</hi> hath by thoſe <hi>Independant vermine</hi> that bred out of the putrifacton of it; been anatomiz'd and quite diſmembred ſince, there is
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:118090:34"/> no man that is not <hi>deafe</hi> and <hi>blind</hi> that can be uninformd.</p>
               <p>Now that ſuch a <hi>martird mooncalfe</hi> canſtil be a living <hi>Parliament</hi> I am ſure there is no man <hi>wakes</hi> that can be ſo perſwaded; eſpeciallie the King that calld it being dead, which both the <hi>law</hi> &amp; <hi>cuſtom</hi> tells you, that a <hi>Parliament</hi> could neuer yet ſurvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve: upon which concluſion you muſt needs grant that his preſent <hi>Majeſtie</hi> (who hath already confirmed by <hi>his;</hi> both my <hi>Lord Lieutenant,</hi> and all that his <hi>Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency</hi> hath don by his <hi>Royal fathers Commiſsion)</hi> hath now indiſputably reverted to him the power to manage a war, and conclude or con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>irme a <hi>peace</hi> in <hi>Irland</hi> except that you will ſtill maintainé that the authoritie of the late <hi>Parliament</hi> is by I know not what <hi>legierdemain</hi> tranſlated into thoſe <hi>uſurpers,</hi> that have not only deſtrojed that <hi>Parliament</hi> but alſo declared that they intend there ſhall never be any more; and this <hi>non conſequence</hi> if you ſtill inſiſt upon, I will conclude you are <hi>crackt</hi> as was that <hi>Spanish gallant</hi> and leave you in your queſt of <hi>Windmills.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But if you can prevayle with your ſelfe to be ſo <hi>ingenuous</hi> as acknowledg the <hi>preceding</hi> truths, I will hold on ſtill, and endevour to remove out of your <hi>ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der conſcience</hi> your laſt and greateſt difficult of <hi>breach of truſt:</hi> indeed a ſcruple very ſuitable to a man of honour ſuch as I would willinglie take you for; and to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin the worke I muſt tell you that the premiſſes are very convinceing that in your compliance with my <hi>Lord Lieutenant</hi> there is no truſt broken either with <hi>God,</hi> or <hi>King,</hi> or <hi>Parliament</hi> (who are all you can pretend to owe a faith unto) by deſerting thoſe <hi>villanous impoſtors,</hi> who have ſupplanted <hi>religion</hi> ſubverted <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy,</hi> murthered the <hi>King,</hi> violated the <hi>Parliament</hi> annihilated the <hi>lawes,</hi> tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled upon <hi>learning</hi> and <hi>nobility,</hi> and left neither <hi>worth</hi> nor <hi>juſtice</hi> unoppreſt within their reach; which kind of perfidious people ſurely to deceive right <hi>reaſon</hi> it ſelfe tells you there is no deceipt.</p>
               <p>Yet had you no ſuch aſſurance I ſhould thinke it ſtrange, that you who have ſtretcht your <hi>Conſcience</hi> ſo <hi>often</hi> &amp; ſo <hi>far</hi> already, as firſt to <hi>breake your truſt</hi> with the <hi>King</hi> when by ſeverall oathes both as a <hi>gowne man</hi> &amp; a <hi>ſwordman</hi> you had oblidged your faith unto him; then with <hi>religion</hi> which conſidered with your education, parents, and a long profeſsion, we may ſay (&amp; not improperly) that it was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by nature convayed into you; after, with that <hi>late carcaſe of a Parliament</hi> from whom you tooke both <hi>Commiſsions</hi> and <hi>employment;</hi> and laſtly with that <hi>presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian Senate</hi> that preferd you hither as a <hi>proſelite</hi> of theirs, ſhould I ſay now make a ſcruple of breaking with <hi>theſe wretches,</hi> to whom you can pretend no other tye, but a <hi>Confraternity in treacherie and miſcheife.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is not your repetition of <hi>Rebells</hi> and <hi>bloody Rebells</hi> will ſerve for your excuſe, ſince that you your ſelfe are ingaged with thoſe <hi>rebells</hi> that have waded dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per into <hi>blood,</hi> and committed <hi>murther</hi> even with the <hi>ſword of Iuſtice</hi> upon not only innocent but <hi>Royall blood;</hi> more impudently, and more in humanly then any people how barbarous ſoever that as yet have breathed under the face of heaven.</p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:118090:34"/>
               <p>'Tis true there hath been much <hi>barbarity</hi> and <hi>cruelty</hi> acted in this Kingdom ſince theſe <hi>unhappy tumults</hi> in the midſt of <hi>confuſion</hi> and <hi>diſorder,</hi> but nothing done under the forme of a <hi>miſcheivous law</hi> or the colour of <hi>abuſed Iuſtice,</hi> againſt any body; much leſſe againſt the life, or perſon of a <hi>King,</hi> and the <hi>best of Kings,</hi> ſuch as thoſe whom you will needes profeſs a faith unto have butchered on a <hi>ſcaffold,</hi> with a hitherto unequalld villany, which without all doubt heaven to convince the world that there is a <hi>divinity</hi> and <hi>juſtice</hi> there, will certainly when his indignation towards us is in ſome meaſure ſatisfied, at laſt ſee <hi>Notoriouſly punished</hi> upon them, and all their <hi>abettors</hi> with ſcourges as much tranſcending ours, as do their crimes.</p>
               <p>And in order to this <hi>juſt revenge</hi> it wil be vertue in the <hi>King</hi> and my <hi>Lord Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant</hi> (which as your ſelfe confeſſes will be a ſin in you circumſtances conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red) not onely to forgive but court <hi>Father Reyley</hi> (&amp; if there be any others of his party leſſe pardonable and leſſe avowable then hee) unto their <hi>duty</hi> whom you can pretend to do nothing with in your <hi>Intrigues</hi> but either confirme them in their <hi>preſent,</hi> or ingage them in a <hi>new rebellion</hi> worſe and more malitious then that they are alreadie plunged in, and which they (being a <hi>trampled</hi> and <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed people,</hi> of another <hi>nation</hi> and <hi>religion</hi> from their <hi>Soveraigne)</hi> leapt at firſt into, out of a general feare, and ſenſe of their particular wrongs from, and aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions to thoſe, who frequently miſuſed upon them both their <hi>own power</hi> and the <hi>Kings authoritie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For the reſtitution of whoſe <hi>juſt Soveraignty,</hi> and the preſervation of <hi>whoſe life,</hi> my <hi>Lord Lieutenant</hi> (whom you expres a ſhamleſſe impudencie to accuſe with any guilt of his deſtruction hath run greater <hi>adventures in his perſon,</hi> made more <hi>prudent eſſaies,</hi> and under went the <hi>hazard of a better fortune</hi> then any ſubject in the three Kingdoms had to looſe beſides; againſt whom your inference is very ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge, that becauſe by the <hi>Kings</hi> own <hi>direction</hi> &amp; <hi>Commiſsion</hi> he endevoured to ſet on foot the <hi>Royall intereſt</hi> again, he muſts need be guilty of, what was acted by thoſe that (before he left <hi>France,</hi> or appeard the ſecond time here about it) had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready robd <hi>the King</hi> of his <hi>libertie,</hi> and actually declared againſt his <hi>life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But they having ſince <hi>ravisht</hi> from his <hi>Majeſtie</hi> his <hi>life</hi> aſwell as <hi>liberty,</hi> and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away both his <hi>Crowne</hi> and <hi>Royall head</hi> together, ſo contrarie to your then declared opinion (delivered as your ſelfe confeſſes to my <hi>Lord Lieutenant</hi> when the <hi>army</hi> firſt Seized on the <hi>perſon of the King</hi> who as you there profeſſed to belei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve intended nothing elſe but to ſecure him from <hi>attempts</hi> &amp; <hi>danger)</hi> muſt needs be a motive ſufficient either to <hi>Convert</hi> you from adhering longer unto them, or an argument at leaſt to <hi>convince</hi> me and all the world, that you both approved of, and conſented to, what ever they have done: how forraine ſoever you ſeeme to make it to your <hi>charge,</hi> in a <hi>Citty</hi> where, and at a <hi>time</hi> when, if you ſhould own it you might well feare to pull the indignation of the people, and a certain deſtruction upon your own head.</p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:118090:35"/>
               <p>Yet ſurely you would much more have plaid the man of honor to have laide aſide theſe <hi>groſſer cheats</hi> &amp; <hi>Mummeries,</hi> &amp; dealing plainly to haue avowed the <hi>bare faced Truth</hi> (as your <hi>great maſters</hi> in <hi>England</hi> have found the courage and the confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to do) that it is neither your care of the <hi>proteſtant Religion,</hi> or <hi>English In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt,</hi> neither your <hi>duty to the Parliament,</hi> nor <hi>tendernes in breach of truſt,</hi> that holds you from ſubmitting to the <hi>King</hi> &amp; my <hi>Lord Lieutenant</hi> but your over conſciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of your own paſt <hi>unfaithfulnes and ingratitude</hi> to thoſe you had ſo many ties unto, your <hi>deſpaire</hi> of a full and free forgivenes, your obſervation that <hi>villany</hi> now a daies is only proſperous, and your conception that the courſe you are in ſutes more with your <hi>miſtaken Intereſt &amp; wild ambitions</hi> then returning to your duty would; laſtly your deſire to continue <hi>yourſelfe</hi> and <hi>that Sr. Politicke,</hi> your moſt reverend brother, there <hi>A Moſes and Aron</hi> to the <hi>Irish Iſralites</hi> to conduct them ſafe out of the <hi>boggs and woods</hi> of their <hi>fortunes</hi> and <hi>eſtates</hi> through the <hi>deſerts of delinqnency;</hi> untill they ſtript of all thoſe cumberſom impediments were rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy for the <hi>land</hi> of <hi>promiſe,</hi> and you laden with their <hi>Egiptian ſpoiles,</hi> and a good old age were fit to be tranſplanted from <hi>Dublin</hi> to the government of the <hi>new Ieruſalem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But let me now at laſt before it be too late prevayle with you ſo far as to perſwade your ſelfe that it is never too late to <hi>mend,</hi> that both the <hi>King</hi> and my <hi>Lord Lieutenant</hi> have mercy and generoſity enough to <hi>forgive</hi> and <hi>forget</hi> all your paſt tranſgreſsions, that <hi>fortune</hi> (how hopefully ſoever ſhe ſeem to looke upon you) hath neither leaſed out her wheeles unto your <hi>Chariot,</hi> nor <hi>victory</hi> intailed her ſelfe unto you <hi>Enſignes</hi> ſo, as to encourage you to that confidence and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption you do put on; forgetting that <hi>God Almightie</hi> doth frequently lull in ſecurity and beſot with their paſt and preſent proſperities thoſe that are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned for a <hi>headlong deſtruction:</hi> and laſtly that (how ſuccesfull ſoever it may be for a time) there is a <hi>fulnes of iniquity</hi> which men being once arrived unto, <hi>Gods judgments</hi> are never long behind. Which <hi>exuberance of ſin</hi> if any people ever attai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned unto, ſurely it is they that have been either <hi>actors</hi> in, or <hi>abettors</hi> of, the <hi>murther of the King:</hi> of the guilt of which horrid crime, that you may cleare your ſelfe, and prevent the hevy judgment that infallibly attends it by a ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable <hi>ſubmiſsion</hi> and returning to your <hi>duty,</hi> is all that he aimes at, who hath dealt thus freely with you; and who on <hi>that ſcore</hi> will be moſt really.</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sr.</salute>
                  <signed>Your very humble ſervaunt. EDWARD WALSINGHAM.</signed>
                  <dateline>Roſcoman Caſtle <date>Iune the 14. 1849.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="letters">
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:118090:35"/>
            <head>The ſeverall <hi>Papers</hi> concerning <hi>Cromwells Paſſe</hi> to my <hi>Lord Lieutenant.</hi> Mentioned PAG. 48.</head>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Dean Boyles,</hi> Letter to my <hi>Lord Lieutenant</hi> touching the tranſactions with <hi>Cromwell</hi> in behalfe of the disbanded <hi>English.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>May it pleaſe your <hi>Excellency</hi>
                  </salute>
               </opener>
               <p>BEing now returned from the enemies quarters, I am bold to give your <hi>Lordship</hi> an account of what we have done there; we were two dayes held in ſuſpence by Generall <hi>Cronwell</hi> whether he would deſcend to any capitula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon thoſe articles we delivered him, dureing which time, his argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments were few, but his perſwaſions many, to come in upon a Cleare ſcore without any articling for conditions, and that he ſayd would put the whole party into a Condition of being truſted by the Parliament, which their inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting upon articles would deprive them of; But we, wholy waving the force of his perſwaſions, told him that we were limited by inſtructions, and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline them in any particular, were very unfaithfull, and beyond our <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion,</hi> we therefore deſired his poſitive reſolution, whether he would aſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine them of their ſecurities, or the like, or no, that ſo we might returne with an account to them that ſent us, whereupon <hi>ireton</hi> objected that by thoſe propoſals, which wee gave in to them, our deſign might be to contract for the Lord <hi>Inchiquint</hi> eſtate, aſwell as others, he being under your <hi>Excellencies</hi> command, to which I made him this anſwer, that indeed it was much the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires of the Officers to ſerve him in that particular, but that I had peremptory directions from his <hi>Lordship</hi> to ſignify unto them that it was not your <hi>Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies</hi> intent, or his <hi>Lordships</hi> to Capitulate with then at all, or to be comprized under any general Conditions, whereuphn <hi>Cromwell</hi> then made anſwer, that if that were our purpoſe he would not a jot the more decline the buſineſſe; There were many houres waſted in debate. before we came to any iſſue, at laſt the reſult of all determined in theſe incloſed conditions, wherin your <hi>Excellency</hi> may he pleaſed to obſerve, that there lyes no obligation at all on our partes, but all on theirs, ſo that your <hi>Excellency</hi> may diſpoſe of your men, or any number of them, as you ſhall thinke fitting, notwithſtanding any enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gements
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:118090:36"/> from us, only thus much we are obliged to, that our party under the couert of thoſe articles, do not prejudice them in the ſurpriſal of any of their guarriſons, or the like, which emboldens me to beſeech your <hi>Excellency,</hi> that <hi>Sr. Thomas Armſtrong</hi> may take notice of it, and ſend his engagement hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for <hi>Sr. Robert Sterlings,</hi> and <hi>Lieutenant Collonel Daniells</hi> ſecurity, and <hi>mine,</hi> this incloſed to him I held it my duty to preſent open to your Excellencie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſent it to himſelfe. My <hi>Lord</hi> Dureing my being there, I had many oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities, and hints given me by Generall <hi>Cromwell,</hi> and <hi>Ireton</hi> whereby I might plainly underſtand that if I would move any thing from your <hi>Excellency,</hi> or the Lord <hi>Inchiquin</hi> they would willingly hearken to it, but I waved them all ſo far that they at laſt in <hi>plain English</hi> asked mee what <hi>your Lordship</hi> intended to doe, if this party came of: I ſaid I was not acquainted with your reſolutions, But that I beleeud you would endeavour to forme the army there into a conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable body, if upon the comeing off of the <hi>English</hi> party, you did not find their behaviours to be ſuch, as might give you no great confidence of them, &amp; ſo enforce you to deſert them, if you were not neceſsitated to tarry with them for want of convenient tranſportation; to which they inſinuated unto me, that I might have a <hi>Paſſe</hi> for your ſafe going of, if you had a mind to it, &amp; that I deſired it; my reply was that I had no commiſsion to that purpoſe, but on the contrary had poſitive directions not to aske any thing in your <hi>Lordship,</hi> or the <hi>Lord Inchiquins</hi> behalfe, yet if they would deliver me any ſuch paſſes for your <hi>Excellency,</hi> and the <hi>Lord Inchiquin,</hi> I would reſerve them by mee, and if I had any opportunity, make uſe of them; the <hi>Paſſes</hi> I have here to diſpoſe of as your <hi>Excellency</hi> ſhall appoint My Lord <hi>Inchiquin</hi> doth exceedingly diſlike my bringing them at all, and the rather, be cauſe there is not included in them a liberty for the ſhip it ſelfe, and all others to goe with you, that have an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to wayte upon you: But J find if your Excellency have any inclination to make uſe of ſuch a <hi>Paſſe,</hi> it might eaſily be gayned for any, that ſhall deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re it, either for my Lord <hi>Muskery;</hi> or my Lord <hi>Taaffe,</hi> or any other officer of quality; They ſay they are very much concerned for the Marquis of <hi>Clan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricard</hi> and if he would but deſire any thing that lyes in their power to ſerve him, he ſhould find that the State of <hi>England</hi> would not be unmindfull of thoſe many good offices (they were informed) he had done for the <hi>poor Proteſtants</hi> in that country. They gave me likewiſe a hint concerning <hi>Sr. Georg Hamilton,</hi> and the <hi>Caſtle</hi> of <hi>Nenagh,</hi> but I took no notice of it. Vpon diſcourſe with <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Cromwell,</hi> he ſayd that he had no intereſt at all in your eſtate, nor any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne upon it: he pretends to be a great ſervant of <hi>your ladies,</hi> and much to pitty her condition, the eſtate which ſhe brought your Lordſhip, they openly profeſſe, ſhall not be given to any from her. The day before I came from thence, there came a pacquet, which gave them ſome ſeeming diſturbance, upon the obſervance whereof, I uſed meanes by one of their own party to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:118090:36"/> with the captaine that brought it, who certifyed him that the news was very bad, and that <hi>Montroſe</hi> was landed, or certainly did intend to land in <hi>Ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> with 12000. men, ſomething of conſequence there is in it, but whether this be the Certainty thereof, or no, it is not yet known. I muſt beg your Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencies pardon for this tedious, and rude diverſion, which I could very much lengthen by ſeverall other paſſages, but I fear I have tranſgreſſed too farr already, which ſubmitting to your <hi>Excellencies</hi> Charitable interpretation, I remain.</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>My Lord,</salute>
                  <signed>Your <hi>Excellencies</hi> moſt faithfull and moſt humble ſervant, M. BOYLE.</signed>
                  <dateline>Clare <date>30. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pril 1650.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Cromwells</hi> Paſſe unto my <hi>Lord Lieutenant.</hi>
               </head>
               <byline>By the <hi>Lord Lieutenant</hi> of <hi>Irland,</hi>
               </byline>
               <p>THeſe are to require you, and every of you, to permit and ſuffer his <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency</hi> the Lord Marquis of <hi>Ormond,</hi> and his family (not exceeding the number of twenty perſons) with three horſes, and alſo their clothes, hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhold ſtuffe, and other goods (not being merchandize) quietly, and ſafely to take ſhipping at any place within the river of <hi>Shannon,</hi> or at <hi>Galloway,</hi> or to Paſſe to <hi>Kinſale,</hi> and take ſhipping there, and from ſuch place of their ſhipping to be tranſported to any parts beyond the ſeas, (except to <hi>England, Wales</hi> or <hi>Scotland)</hi> without any violence, injury or moleſtation, as you will anſwer the Contrary at your perills. <hi>Provided</hi> they take ſhipping, and depart from <hi>Irland</hi> within the ſpace of two monthes after the date hereof, and that in the mean time they, or any of them do not act any thing to the prejudice of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or <hi>Commonwealth</hi> of <hi>England. Given</hi> under my hand, and ſeale the ſeaventh day of <hi>May,</hi> Anno Dom. 1650.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>O. CROMWEL.</signed>
               </closer>
               <trailer>To all <hi>Officers</hi> ſouldiers and others under my command, &amp; to all <hi>Captaines</hi> &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders of any of the <hi>shipping</hi> under the obedience of the <hi>Parliament.</hi>
               </trailer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:118090:37"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Dean Boyles</hi> ſecond Letter to my <hi>Lord Lieutenant</hi> to juſtify himſelfe concerning the fore mentioned <hi>Paſſe,</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>May it pleaſe your <hi>Excellency.</hi>
                  </salute>
               </opener>
               <p>REflecting upon the preſent ſad Condition of thoſe, who have adhered unto his <hi>Majeſties</hi> ſervice, I aſſumed to my ſelfe very much ſatisfaction (above many others) in the Clearneſſe of my deportments therein, which hitherto hath alwayes juſtified me in the opinion of thoſe, who have been en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted in the mannagement of his affaires; But I find by ſome Letters of your <hi>Excellencies</hi> to my Lord <hi>Inchiquin</hi> that I now ly under ſome hazard of being blaſted in your <hi>Excellencies</hi> eſteeme, by a ſevere charge layd on my diſcretion, and a greater wound upon my integrity, as if I had exceeded the limits of my <hi>Commiſsion,</hi> in this laſt, (and I may juſtly call it unfortunat) tranſaction: <hi>My Lord,</hi> my pretence is ſo ſlender to the firſt of theſe, that I can very eaſily diſgeſt any thing, that is objected me on that ſcore, being much more ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of my own weaknes, then any other man can bee, though J cannot yet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince my ſelfe of any ſin againſt the rules of reaſon: for apprehending When I left your <hi>Excellency,</hi> that it was your reſolution to depart the Kingdome, and finding the intentions of the enemy to block up that Harbour, by their ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, from whence you purpoſed your departure, I eſteemed it a ſpeciall peice of providence for the preſervation of your <hi>perſon,</hi> and your <hi>honour,</hi> that they by an accidental diſcourſe ſhould offer that of themſelves, which I ſuſpected you might have been neceſsitated to make ſuite for; As for that clauſe in the <hi>Paſſe</hi> obligeing you not to act any thing to their diſadvantage, during your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder here, though I muſt confeſſe that to be no way ſuitable to your Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies condition, yet I conceive it may juſtly excuſe my acceptance of it, I not making it at all my buſines to ſeeke it, and might therefore appear imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent, and indeed injurious to your <hi>Excellency</hi> to except againſt it, which I the rather paſt over out of an opinion that your <hi>Excellency</hi> would have declined the ſervice here, by the time of my returne out of their quarters. But for this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular as it intrencheth onely upon (that which I cannot own) diſcretion; I ſubmit it wholy to your <hi>Excellencies</hi> better diſquiſition, having this ſanctuary at laſt to be my refuge, that if I have tranſgreſſd therein, it had no other de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign in it, but your <hi>Excellencies</hi> preſervation, and honour. But as to the other particular of exceeding, my <hi>Commiſsion,</hi> I muſt beſeech your <hi>Excellencies</hi> leave a litle to juſtify my integrity, the rather in that I look upon my ſelfe out of any Capacity to ſerve you hereafter, whilſt I ly under the juſtice of that reproofe,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:118090:37"/> diſhoneſty being an offence which J abhominate towards the moſt ordinary perſon, much more towards your <hi>Excellency,</hi> who have layd ſo many obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions upon me; I had nothing in Charge from your <hi>Excellency</hi> in the tranſaction of that buſines, but to declare your refuſall of comeing to any conditions with them at all, or of having any inclinations there unto, which I did oftentimes not privately, or to the meaneſt of them, but publiquely, to the cheifeſt amongſt them, <hi>Cromwell</hi> and <hi>Ireton.</hi> Which I conceive to he a perfect diſcharge of what was intruſted to me by your <hi>Excellency,</hi> and as for my bare reception of the <hi>Paſſe,</hi> as it proceeded not at all from my demand, ſo it cannot certainly, without very much ſeverity, be interpreted a breach of my <hi>Commiſsion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This poor party being very ſuddainly to be diſperſed to their ſeverall deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, I know not what providence intends mee for the future, but for the preſent I am like to be neceſsitated to the ſame misfortune with them, and by this great miſtake of my eſſayes for their ſervice, to be inforced to deſert the perſons whom I honour, and to retire amongſt thoſe, who are, and have been my moſt profeſſed enemies. I know not when I ſhall have the opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to wayte next upon your <hi>Excellency,</hi> and have therefore aſſumed the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence of giving your <hi>Excellency</hi> the trouble of this my juſt excuſe; if it may prevayle to reeſtabliſh me in your <hi>Excellencies</hi> good opinion, it wil afford mee many peacefull thoughts, while I continue in my baniſhment. However, as I was your <hi>Excellencies</hi> moſt faithfull ſervant, before you placed and of your favours on mee, ſo no miſinterpretation of my actions ſhall make me a whitt decline my unalterable reſolution of avowing my ſelfe.</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>My Lord,</salute>
                  <signed>Your Excellencies <hi>moſt obedient and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſervant.</hi> M, BOYLE.</signed>
                  <dateline>Cloenraud <date>May 9. 1650.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The <hi>Governour</hi> of <hi>Roſſe</hi> his Letter to <hi>Generall Preſton</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding in <hi>Waterford.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>My Lord.</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>HAving had experience of your <hi>Lordships</hi> honour, and civility, and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the condition of the place under your command, what by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagicuſnes
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:118090:38"/> within your citty, and the ſword about it, and the regardles inconfiderablenes of your party for your releife, induces me to ſympathize with your <hi>Lordship,</hi> J haveing now a ſeaſonable opportunity to offer ſuch conditions to your Lordſhip, as may befit ſuch a perſon of honour to accept hereof, and blemiſhes; and objections being removed, you have no leſſe <hi>preſidents</hi> then the Lord of <hi>Ormond,</hi> and the Lord of <hi>Inchiquin;</hi> Their <hi>Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners,</hi> and the Lord Lieutenant Generall <hi>Cromwell</hi> for each, and in behalfe of both parties have concluded for their Comming in to the Lord Lieutenant Generall <hi>Cromwell,</hi> and to take up armes that will, others to goe beyond ſeas, with their equipage within two monthes. This was confirmd, and ratifyed laſt <hi>Friday</hi> at <hi>Fetherd.</hi> And I would not tell you a falſe thing for <hi>Rockes</hi> of <hi>pearle;</hi> If you pleaſe to be ſo fortunate to your <hi>ſelfe,</hi> and <hi>family,</hi> as to adhere to this offer here incloſed they ſhall be confirmd under the Lord <hi>Cromwells</hi> hand, and ſeale, upon the capitulation, and agreement betwixt your Lordſhip, and my ſelfe, for the ſurrender of the <hi>Citty</hi> to the uſe of the <hi>ſtate</hi> of <hi>England;</hi> If you pleaſe, I ſhall meet you for a perſonall treaty, where you ſhall appoint for better ſatisfaction, and during our meeting, or going from it, no acts of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtility to be comitted on either ſide, of which I aſſure to your Lordſhip if your Lordſhip promiſe the like to mee; And for the Citizens they ſhall have the ſame conditions, as <hi>Roſſe</hi> had, which is now a <hi>Flouriſhing</hi> place. In tendernes to your <hi>Lordship,</hi> and the <hi>Citty,</hi> that both may be preſerved, and in a happy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, I did prevayle to make theſe overtures, and negotiation, deſiring your <hi>Lordships</hi> anſwer I remain.</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>My Lord,</salute>
                  <signed>Your <hi>Lordships</hi> humble ſervant. D, AXTEL.</signed>
                  <dateline>Roſſe <date>April 30. 1650.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Dean Boyles</hi> Letter to <hi>Cromwell</hi> about the <hi>Paſſes</hi> he recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from him.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>My Lord,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I preſume your <hi>Lordship</hi> remembers upon what ſcore the <hi>Paſſes</hi> for the <hi>Lord Lieutenant,</hi> and Lord <hi>Inchiquin</hi> were received by mee from your <hi>Lordship</hi>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:118090:38"/> upon a ſuſpicion I had there might fall out ſome unhandſome cariage towards them, upon the departure of theſe <hi>English</hi> out of the quarters; which oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity of ſerving them, I was not very unwilling to imbrace, conceiving it an honourable expedient for their ſecurity, in caſe they ſhould be neceſsitated thereunto. But I find His <hi>Excellency</hi> it not at all ſatisfyed with me therin, I having no <hi>Commiſsion</hi> to that purpoſe, and upon intimation ſent his <hi>Lordship</hi> that I had ſuch a thing, he commanded me to returne it with civility to your <hi>Lordship;</hi> But finding by the Copy of a Letter to the Governor of <hi>Waterford</hi> (which I here incloſe) that there is ſome uſe indeavoured to be made thereof to his exceeding preiudice, and diſhonour, <hi>he</hi> hath commanded metoſend it to himſelfe leaſt the <hi>returne</hi> of it ſhould be perverted to his prejudice, as the <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance</hi> was; I have hereby returned your <hi>Lordship</hi> the <hi>Paſſe</hi> for the Lord <hi>Inchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quin,</hi> and from both have received very ſlender thankes for bringing them. Your Lordſhip knows I made no engagement for any thing no either of their behalfes, but on the contrary in the diſcuſsion of thoſe propoſaIls, which I preſented to your <hi>Lordship</hi> from the Officers, did declare, that I had poſitive commands to except the Lord Marquis of <hi>Ormond,</hi> and Lord of <hi>Iuchiquin,</hi> from having any benefit of, or relation unto any thing, that was comprized in that <hi>treaty,</hi> ſo that the ſuggeſtions of <hi>M. Axtell</hi> to the Governor of <hi>Waterford,</hi> though they are nothing a greable to the conditions we received from your Lordſhip, yet they give a very great diſſatisfaction to many here of my integrity, as pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming me to act ſome thing under hand, either by deſign, or beyond Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion wherein if your <hi>Excellency,</hi> would be pleaſed to afford me the juſtice of ſome kind of vindication, it would extremly oblige me in a very gratefull reſentiment.</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>My Lord,</salute>
                  <signed>Your <hi>Excellencies</hi> humble ſervant. M. BOYLE.</signed>
                  <dateline>Cloneraud <date>May 3. 1656.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:118090:39"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>My</hi> Lord Lieutenants <hi>Letter to</hi> Cromwell <hi>when he ſent him Back his</hi> Paſſe.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SR.</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <hi>DEan Boyle</hi> having brought me a <hi>Paper</hi> ſigned, and ſealed by you, ſeeming to be a <hi>Paſſe</hi> for me to tranſport my ſelfe beyond ſeas; I did much wonder from whence, or for what reaſon it was, that you either gave, or he accepted it; ſince he was directed to declare to you (if it came in queſtion) that I had no intention to treat with you for <hi>a Paſſe,</hi> or any other thing; And though I am yet to ſeek a reaſon for his part of that tranſaction, yet yours appeares to me in <hi>Axtells</hi> Letter to <hi>Generall Preſton;</hi> I have by this Trumpetter returned you your <hi>Paper,</hi> and for your unſought courteſy do aſſure you, that when you shall deſire a <hi>Paſſe</hi> from me, and I <hi>thinke fit</hi> to grant it, I shall not make uſe of it to corrupt any that commands under you, I remain.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your humble ſervant. ORMONDE.</signed>
                  <dateline>Kogh reogh <date>the 17, May 1650.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="speech">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:118090:39"/>
               <head>The <hi>Speech</hi> of his Excellency the <hi>Marquis of Ormond</hi> unto the <hi>Generall Aſſembly</hi> of the <hi>confederates</hi> in <hi>Irland</hi> upon the ſigning of the <hi>peace,</hi> in anſwer to the <hi>Oration</hi> of <hi>Sr. Richard Blake</hi> Chairman of the <hi>Aſſembly.</hi> Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned. PAG. 55.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>My Lords and Gentlemen.</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Shall not ſpeake to thoſe expreſsions of <hi>duty</hi> and <hi>Loyalty,</hi> ſo eloquently di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted into a Diſcourſe, by the Gentleman appointed by you to deliver your ſenſe, you will preſently have in your hands greater and more ſolid Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments of His <hi>Majeſties</hi> gratious acceptance of them, then I can <hi>enumerate,</hi> or then perhaps, you your ſelves <hi>diſcerne,</hi> for, beſides the proviſion made againſt your remoteſt feares of the ſeverity of certaine <hi>Lawes,</hi> and beſides many other freedomes, and bounties conveighed to you, and your poſterity, by theſe <hi>Articles,</hi> There is a doore, and that a large one, not left, but ſett open to give you entrance, by your future merits, to whatſoever of <hi>honour,</hi> or other <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage,</hi> you can reaſonably wiſh, ſo that you have in preſent fruition what may abundantly ſatisfye, and yet there are no bounds ſet to your <hi>hopes</hi> but you are rather invited, or, (according to a new Phraſe, but to an old &amp; better pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe) You ſeeme to <hi>have a Call from Heaven,</hi> to excerciſe your Armes and utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt fortitude, in the <hi>nobleſt,</hi> and <hi>juſteſt Cauſe</hi> the world hath knowen; for let all the Circumſtances, incident to a great &amp; good Cauſe of warr, be examined, and they will befound Comprehended in that which you are now called war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantably to defende; <hi>Religion,</hi> not in the narrow circumſcribed definition of it, <hi>under</hi> this, or that late found out <hi>diſtinction,</hi> but <hi>Chriſtian Religion,</hi> is our Quarrell, which certainly is as much and as fatally ſtruck at (I may ſay more) by the <hi>blaſphemous Lycence</hi> of this Age, then ever it was by the rudeſt Incurſions of the moſt barbarous and moſt avowed Enemys to <hi>Chriſtianity.</hi> The <hi>venerable Lawes,</hi> and fundamentall Conſtitutions are trodden under impious, and, for
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:118090:40"/> the moſt, part <hi>Mechanique feete.</hi> 
                  <note n="a" place="bottom">Iudg reader if theſe be the words of one that intends to betray the <hi>Kingdome</hi> and <hi>Kings</hi> intereſt to <hi>Cromwell.</hi>
                  </note> The <hi>ſacred perſon</hi> of the <hi>King</hi> (the life of thoſe <hi>Lawes)</hi> under an ignominious impriſonment, &amp; his life threatned to be taken away by the <hi>Sacrilegious hands</hi> of the <hi>baſeſt</hi> of the People that owe Him obediences, And, to endeare the Quarrell to you, the <hi>fountaine</hi> of all the benefits you have but now acknowledged, and of what you may further hope for by this Peace, and your owne merits, is now in danger to be obſtructed by the <hi>execrable mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> of the <hi>worthjeſt Prince</hi> that ever ruld theſe <hi>Iſlands.</hi> In ſhort, <hi>Hell</hi> can adde no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to the deſperate <hi>Miſcheife</hi> now openly projected.</p>
               <p>And now judge, if a greater, or a more <hi>glorious feild</hi> was ever ſet open to action; and then prepare yourſelves to enter into it, And receive theſe few Advices from <hi>one</hi> throughly embarqued with you in the <hi>Adventure.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt.</hi> Let me recommend unto you, that to this, as to all other <hi>holy Actions,</hi> you would prepare yourſelves with <hi>perfect Charity,</hi> a <hi>Charity</hi> that may obliterate whatſoever <note n="b" place="bottom">Are not here the <hi>factions.</hi>
                  </note> of <hi>Rancours</hi> a long continued <hi>Civill warr</hi> may have contracted in you againſt any that ſhall now cooperate with you in ſo bleſſed a <hi>worke,</hi> &amp; let his engagement with you, (who ever he is) <hi>be,</hi> as it ought to be, a <hi>Bond</hi> of <hi>Unity,</hi> of <hi>Love,</hi> of <hi>Concord,</hi> ſtronger then the <hi>neareſt tye</hi> of nature.</p>
               <p>In the <hi>next</hi> place, <hi>marke,</hi> and <hi>beware</hi> of thoſe that ſhall goe about to <hi>renew,</hi> or <hi>create</hi> 
                  <note n="c" place="bottom">Iealouſies.</note> 
                  <hi>Iealouſies</hi> in you, under what pretenſe, ſoever, &amp; accompt ſuch as <hi>infernal Miniſters,</hi> imployed to promote the <hi>black Deſigne</hi> on foote, to ſubvert <hi>Monarchy,</hi> &amp; to make us all <hi>ſlaves</hi> to thoſe that are ſo to theire owne <hi>avaritious Luſts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Away,</hi> aſſoone &amp; as much as poſsibly may be, with thoſe <hi>diſtinctions</hi> 
                  <note n="d" place="bottom">And <hi>nationall animoſities</hi> fore ſeen &amp; forelold that ſince have ruind all.</note> 
                  <hi>of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> and of <hi>Partys,</hi> which are the feilds where in the ſeede of thoſe <hi>Rankor weeds</hi> are ſowen by the great <hi>Enemy</hi> of our <hi>Peace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the <hi>laſt</hi> place, Lett us all diveſt ourſelves of that <hi>prepoſterous,</hi> that <hi>ridiculous Ambition,</hi> and ſelfe <hi>Intereſt,</hi> which rather leads to our threatned generall <hi>Ruine,</hi> then to the <hi>enjoyment</hi> of <hi>Advantages</hi> unſeaſonably deſired.</p>
               <p>And if at any time you ſhall thinke yourſelves <hi>pincht</hi> to neare the <hi>bone</hi> by thoſe <hi>Taxes,</hi> &amp; <hi>Leavyes</hi> that may be impoſed on you for your <hi>defenſe,</hi> Conſider then, how <hi>vaine,</hi> how <hi>foolish</hi> a thing it will be, to ſtarve a <hi>Righteous Cauſe</hi> for want of <hi>neceſſary ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port;</hi> to preſerve yourſelves <hi>fat &amp; guilded ſacrificies</hi> to the rapine of a <hi>mercileſſe Enemy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And if wee come thus well prepared to a <hi>Contention,</hi> ſo <hi>juſt,</hi> on our part, God will either bleſſe our Endeavours with <hi>ſucceſſe</hi> &amp; <hi>victory,</hi> or <note n="f" place="bottom">Were there ever nobler or more generous expreſsions of <hi>loyalty</hi> then theſe.</note> 
                  <hi>Crowne</hi> our ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings with <hi>honour,</hi> &amp; <hi>patience;</hi> for what <hi>honour</hi> will it not be, if God have ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined of us) to periſhwith a <hi>long glorious Monarchy?</hi> And who can wante <hi>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience</hi> 
                  <note n="e" place="bottom">The people of <hi>Irland</hi> have found the truth of this by a <hi>lamentable experience.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:118090:40"/> to ſuffer with <hi>oppreſt Princes?</hi> But as our <hi>Endeavours,</hi> ſo let our <hi>prayers</hi> be, vigorous, that <hi>they</hi> may be delivered from a more <hi>unnatural Rebellion</hi> then is mentioned by any <hi>ſtory,</hi> now raiſed to the <hi>higheſt pitch of ſucceſse</hi> againſt <hi>them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſhould now ſay ſomething to you for <hi>my ſelfe,</hi> in returne to the advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious mention made of <hi>me,</hi> 
                  <note n="g" place="bottom">Or greater modeſty.</note> &amp; my <hi>Endeavours</hi> to bring this <hi>ſettlement</hi> to paſſe; but I confeſſe my thoughts were wholy taken up with thoſe much <hi>greater Concerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments;</hi> Let it ſuffice, that as I wiſh to be continued in your good <hi>eſteeme</hi> &amp; <hi>affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> ſo I ſhall freely adventure upon any <hi>hazard,</hi> and eſteeme no <hi>trouble</hi> a <hi>diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty</hi> too great to encounter, if I may manifeſt my <hi>zeale</hi> to this <hi>Cauſe,</hi> and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge ſome part of the <hi>obligations</hi> that are upon me to ſerve <hi>this Kingdome.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAg. 6. l. 7. for <hi>Intereſts, of the crown</hi> read <hi>Intereſts of the crown,</hi> P. 7. l. 28. for <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> read <hi>Mounſter.</hi> P. 9. l. 22. for <hi>prece</hi> read <hi>peace.</hi> P. 24. l. 17. after <hi>Col. Birne,</hi> read <hi>The famous Pudſey with the poleaxe, Colonell Walton, Griſſith Cavanagh, &amp;c.</hi> P. 29. l. 16. for <hi>appeared</hi> read <hi>as appeared.</hi> P. 49. l. 3. for <hi>ad</hi> read <hi>a.</hi> P. 50, l. 10. <hi>Clonwell</hi> read <hi>Clonmell.</hi> P 51. l. 3. for <hi>Neavagh</hi> read <hi>Neanagh.</hi> ibid. for <hi>Puachaſes</hi> read <hi>Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſes.</hi> P. 52. for <hi>hande</hi> read <hi>handes.</hi> P. 53. for <hi>that is their</hi> read <hi>that it is their.</hi> P. 56. for <hi>I have given</hi> read I <hi>have here given.</hi> Erratas in the Letters. P. 4. l. 19. for <hi>take thy paines</hi> read <hi>take this Paines</hi> ibid. for <hi>an foyle</hi> read <hi>an unglorious foyle.</hi> P. 6. l. 42. for <hi>it</hi> read <hi>is.</hi> P. 12. l. 1. for <hi>to laide</hi> ad <hi>to have laide</hi> ibid. l. 27. for <hi>is fulneſse</hi> read <hi>is a fulneſſe.</hi> P. 3. l. 8. for <hi>Cronwell</hi> read <hi>Cromwell.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
